<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons one preached at Paules Crosse December 20. By Roger Lea Master of Arts, of Iesus-Colledge in Cambridge: and preacher at S. Leonards Shorditch, in Middlesex, by London. Another preached in Paules-Church, Decemb. 26, being S. Steuens day, by Iohn Squire, Master of Arts, of the same Colledge: and preacher of the same parish</title>
            <author>Ley, Roger, b. 1593 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838842</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838842</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 843:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons one preached at Paules Crosse December 20. By Roger Lea Master of Arts, of Iesus-Colledge in Cambridge: and preacher at S. Leonards Shorditch, in Middlesex, by London. Another preached in Paules-Church, Decemb. 26, being S. Steuens day, by Iohn Squire, Master of Arts, of the same Colledge: and preacher of the same parish</title>
                  <author>Ley, Roger, b. 1593 or 4.</author>
                  <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653. Sermon preached in Pauls church upon Saint Stevens fay. 1618. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. I[ones] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first sermon has a separate title page, with same imprint as general title page, reading: The scepter of righteousnes, a sermon preached at Paules-Crosse. December 20. 1618. By Roger Ley, Master of Art and minister of Gods word in Shorditch.</note>
                  <note>"A sermon preached in Pauls church vpon Saint Stevens day. 1618" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Pagination and signatures continuous.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of I2, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3231:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS, ONE PREACHED AT PAVLES CROSSE DECEMBER 20. BY <hi>ROGER LEA</hi> Maſter of Arts, of <hi>Ieſus</hi>-Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge: and Preacher at <hi>S. Leonards</hi> Shorditch, in Middleſex, by LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANOTHER</hi> Preached in Paules-Church, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 26, <hi>being S.</hi> Steuens <hi>day, by</hi> IOHN SQVIRE, <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> of the ſame Colledge: <hi>and Preacher of the ſame Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVC. 22.38.</hi>
               </bibl> Ecce duo gladii hîc.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by W.I. for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Exchange. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3231:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3231:2"/>
                  <p>THE SCEPTER OF RIGHTEOVSNES.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLES-CROSSE, DECEMBER 20. 1618.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>ROGER LEY,</hi> MASTER OF ARTS, and Miniſter of Gods Word in SHORDITCH.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 45.6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thy throne (O God) is for euer and euer: the ſcepter of thy kingdome is a right ſcepter.</p>
                     <p>Thou loueſt righteouſneſſe, and hateſt iniquitie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, thy God, hath anoynted thee with the oyle of gladneſſe aboue thy fellowes.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Anno Dom. 1619.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3231:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3231:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>SPECTATISSIMO VIRO DOCTORI MOVMFORT IN ECCLESIA Sancti <hi>Pauli</hi> London Canonico Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti, huius vitae foelicitatem &amp; futurae gloriam.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ESTO iam peracto (Vir inſigniſſime) ceſſantibus exparte Eccleſiae veſtrae Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiis, quibus Auditores intenti, ad legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum minus vacârunt, prodit Libellus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Vt qui prius in audiendo fuerunt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupati, iam incipiant fieri Lectores. Si quis igniculos aliquos retineat ex illis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris conceptos: hîc ſi velit animum exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat. Cuius reianſam praebet materia non multum à tempore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiens: agitur enim de perpetuo Saluatoris noſtri regimine: verſumque Textus huius vltimum ex Pſalmo <hi>110.</hi> Apoſtolum citare volunt Interpretes. Qui Pſalmus Natali Dominico legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ab Eccleſia noſtra proponitur. Tractat enim <hi>De virga virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quam ex Sion emittet Dominus.</hi> Fateor quidem me animo non intrepido hoc Opus evulgare: Prelum autem quaſi praelium periculi pleniſſimum reformido. Obiiciant fortaſſe nonnulli iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventutem mihi; ideoque ſilentium quinquennale potius indice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. Quibus nihilominus respondeo, in hac aetate iuvenili quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nnalem taciturnitatem effluxiſſe. Ab initio quoque propoſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram inter <hi>humiles Mirycas</hi> delireſcere niſi grauioribus excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus conſiliis: lenta haecingenii vimina (quae propterea magis flecti poterant) huc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſque ſuſtuliſſem. Si quis praeterea ſortem me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m &amp; locum in Eccleſia mediocrem obiiciat, hunc omitto, nam dona theologica qualiacun que ſunt ab aeſtimatione fortunae &amp; dignitate
<pb facs="tcp:3231:4"/>loci prorſus pendere non debent. Contra hunc error em vt dicam quod cenſeo, Tacendo, ei fauere non eſt virile: quinetiam aptius iudicavi ſcribendo ad confatationem tanti criminis me offerre, Ipſa ſiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idem Poemata hoc ab Authore ſuo exiorſerunt
<q>Fortunam Domini non meru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re ſui.</q> Solus au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em periculoſa haee itinera non ſuſcepi, ſed ab alio quaſi fultus &amp; ſtipatus. Vique ſi ſax haec mea in mari turbido ſe oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, <hi>Hele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a</hi> quaedam &amp; portentum videretur, cum tamen appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo ſub duplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> specie, fortunatos cuentus declarar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mihi videor; nunc autem ſub <hi>Caſtoris</hi> &amp; <hi>Pollucis</hi> titulo bonas interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſperare poſſum. Haec humanitati tuae &amp; doctorum hominum iudiciis credo ſatiſfacere, illis autem quiminus literati buius O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis ſenſum non percipiunt nihil extra concionem afferre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creui. Neceſſe habui contra eruditorum cenſuras ſeueriores ſcuto inſtar <hi>Fab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i</hi> deſenſionem parare. Pro caeteris verò, non eſt tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gendum clypeo <hi>Fabii</hi> quàm gladio <hi>Marcelli:</hi> ſcilicet errores &amp; peccata, ipſa aggredi concione potius, quàm in principio longiores ambages coutexere.</p>
                  <p>Ad te quod ſpectat (reuerende Vir) alius Scriptor cum te multa beneuolentia proſequatur; vt Opus hoc tibi dicarem, horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor erat acerrimus. Nouit enim in me bene merita tua, meque memorem beneficii, etſi mentem alique teſtimonio gratam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probare neglexeram. Accipe igitur in biliothecam tuam ampliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimam paruum hoc animi gratimunuſculum Naturalicurſu par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua flumina ni ingentia maria ſe emittunt: Eadem ratione, mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racerebri fluenta conſeruationem ſui in Oceano tuo deſiderant. Deus te tueatur incolumem, vt prata Domini rigare valeas, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que alios extra laetos Academiae fontes ſitos, ex tua redundanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gratas aſpergines derivare.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Dignitatis tuae cultor amantiſſimus, ROGERVS LEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3231:4"/>
                  <head>THE SCEPTER OF RIGHTEOVSNES.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A ſermon preached at Pauls Croſſe the twentieth day of December, 1618. being the fourth Sunday in Aduent.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. Corinthians 15. verſ. 24, 25.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Then commeth the end, when he ſhall haue deliuered vp the kingdome to God euen the Father, when he ſhall haue put downe all rule, and all authoritie and power. For he muſt reigne till he hath put all enemies vnder his feete.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Scripture is profitable and maketh the man of God perfect ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore the Law of God is called a perfect Law in the nineteenth Pſalme. Not that euery matter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this life and the common affaires of this world muſt bee brought from thence as ſome vpſtart Doctours in our kingdome once did teach: For theſe men not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3231:5"/>knowing how to keepe within compaſſe, haue giuen more then it is capable of. For as one did well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue againſt them, euery part of Scripture may be called perfect, as well as the whole entire body of Scripture: as euery part of a man is perfect for the end it was intended; although it be not the whole man: Among thoſe I haue here propounded a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect part, like vnto the head which conteineth in it all the ſences, and from which the ſinewes doe ſpread themſelues to giue life and motion to the body. The ſtate of heauen: The ſtate of earth: The ſtate of hell in ſome ſort being here deſcribed, The end of this life being ſet downe, and another without end.</p>
                     <p>A gouernment here, by men, there by God: vpon which cauſes is built the frame of our obedience and our due reuerence to the diuine Maieſtie moſt ſurely confirmed. So then you ſee perfection in the text, concerning a perfect expounder; that care concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth me, whome although I finde not of worth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to manage ſo great a prouince: I ground vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his words that ſaid my ſtrength is made perfect in weakeneſſe. Concerning a perfect auditour that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth you: See then how <hi>Cyprian</hi> deſcribes him in the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Donatus. Tam ore, quam mente, totus auditores, &amp; hoc amore quo diligis. An abſolute hearer ſhewes it by a fixed countenance and ſtedfaſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. Secondly, by a minde willing to be taught and to goe away better when the ſermon is done, and thirdly, by a louing minde, to accept well that which is ſpoken, and kindely to cenſure.</hi> If we can thus frame to the text, then may we alſo bring our buſineſſe to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3231:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>I ſhall with proſperous ſpeede be at my end, and if our life be but a ſpanne long as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes, your life is like the ſermon and our time vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally figured by the houre-glaſſe: your end ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow mine, as it is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Pſalme. Thou brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt our yeares to an end as it were a tale that is told. Let our endeauors then concurre, that we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the worke, and enioy that end in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the text. <hi>Then commeth the end, &amp;c.</hi> So may the word of God appeare perfect, for the law of God is a perfect law conuerting the ſoule in the ſeauenth verſe of the forenamed Pſalme, that which is perfect may make perfect: ſhewing in it ſelfe a ſound per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, becauſe it workes in vs a ſincere conuerſion. Theſe words may be taken as an argument of the reſurrection, (among ſundry other reaſons that I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit becauſe of abundance of matter herein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.) For Chriſt muſt be an abſolute king, to honour and aduance his ſubiects into glory by raiſing them vp into life eternall, and confounding his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the laſt whereof is death. And as it augmenteth the glory of a king to reigne a long time, to make a manifeſt and a large declaration of his power, in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ages, and much variety: ſo Chriſt doth not on the ſuddaine end the world, but deferres his accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment thereof til he hath raigned a certaine time, <hi>To put all his enemies vnder his feete.</hi> Secondly, theſe words are for comfort. If any ſhould be ouer haſty to leaue this life, to come to that better <hi>kingdome,</hi> here S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemeth to giue a reaſon of Chriſts long tarrying: we muſt not expect our end before our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3231:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord appoints it, but continue in the field and keepe our rankes againſt the enemies vnder our captaine, till he end the warre and bring vs to a place of reſt. Becauſe as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non eſt conſentaneum medio ſtadio nos coronari, We muſt not enioy our crowne before we runne our race,</hi> but as conſtant runners hold out till we come at the iournies end.</p>
                     <p>We may deuide theſe two verſes in the words of <hi>Aquinus,</hi> here is firſt <hi>adaptio boni, the performing of good, &amp; remotio mali, the remoouing of euill.</hi> Both here by Chriſt are wrought as a patterne to all rulers, that for the time they are in office their conſcience may tell them, this good haue I done, and this euill haue I repreſt. For he that will hurt none, and doe good to none, but thinkes it good ſleeping in a whole skin, and the ſafeſt courſe not to meddle, carrieth a reſolution not worthy the minde of a ſuperiour, but by our <hi>Sauiours</hi> example hee muſt hazard and put forth himſelfe. So in the 24. verſe hee ſets by the good; <hi>Then ſhall be the end when he ſhall haue deliuered vp the kingdome to the Father.</hi> And in the 15. verſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels the bad. <hi>He muſt reigne till he hath put all his enemies vnder his ſeete.</hi> And as <hi>Anchiſes</hi> gaue counſell to his ſonne in the which the Romans ſeemed to bragge for executing the precept.
<q>Parcere ſubiectis &amp; debellare ſuperbos.</q>
                        <note place="margin">Aenec. 6.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To ſpare the ſubiects and to pull downe the proude,</hi> The firſt is practiſed here in the 24. verſe, <hi>parcere ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectis, To ſpare or rather to honour the ſubiects, Then ſhall be the end when he ſhall haue deliuered the kingdome to the Father;</hi> and the ſecond is expreſſed in the 25. verſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3231:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <hi>there he pulls downe the proude. He muſt reigne till hee hath put all his enemies vnder his feete.</hi> Concerning the verſes in themſelues ſeuerally conſidered; In the 24. verſe conſider firſt an end of the old world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Then ſhall be the end,</hi> the eſtate of the new world <hi>he ſhall haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp the kingdome to the Father,</hi> and the manner of gouernment without degrees of ſecular power by God immediately, <hi>He ſhall put downe all rul, and all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power.</hi> In the 25. conſider. <hi>The kingdome, and the conqueſt, the kingdome, he muſt reigne, the Conqueſt, till he hath put all enemies vnder his feete.</hi> In the laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the parties vanquiſhed, <hi>his enemies,</hi> and their miſerable ouerthrow &amp; diſcomfiture <hi>vnder his feete. They are put vnder feete.</hi> In the firſt place we haue the laſt eſtate of all the world to conſider, <hi>Then commeth the end.</hi> In euery buſineſſe the laſt iſſue muſt bee firſt concluded, as in running a race we firſt agree of the end to which the ſwift motion of the courſe muſt aime, and approach. In ſhooting, the marke and ſcope it firſt ſet vp. Therefore it is obſerued that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall ſciences muſt be handled <hi>per methodum analiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fine admedia. We firſt ſet downe the end, and then the meanes that leadeth to the end.</hi> Of ends there are two ſorts, firſt an end of deſtruction; and ſecondly an end of accompliſhment when a thing is finiſhed. The one is a bad end, the other a good, by the one a thing is ended, that is, to ſay conſumed: by the other a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or worke is ended, that is, it is perfected. In this place <hi>Beza</hi> vnderſtands the latter, the world ſhall be ended, that is it ſhall be perfected. But to ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, we may vnderſtand both. For an accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3231:7"/>cannot bee without the deſtruction of ſome thing. <hi>Generatio vnius eſt corruptio alterius, when a new thing is formed, the old thing muſt be altered,</hi> according to the 36. verſe of this chapter. <hi>That which thou ſoweſt is not quickned except it die.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Briefely then of theſe two ends in order. Firſt, the world, and the inhabitants, and all things that we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, muſt haue an end: they muſt be deſtroyed and conſumed. Euery thing that ſeemeth moſt ſtrong and beautifull, muſt in the end vaniſh and fall away. The cauſe of this is ſinne for when things are in their height, they abuſe their time, they beare not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues aright in the middeſt of their glory, the gifts of God are abuſed, and therefore he plagues the earth and deſtroyes the world: men are the abuſers, and therefore that time which giueth them leaue to ſin, bringeth them likewiſe to an end, and burieth them in a common deſtruction. This is the nature of ſinne, it is ſtill a deſtroyer. God did threaten <hi>Adam</hi> in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe at the firſt with <hi>moriendo morieris, in the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt die the death.</hi> And euer ſince where ſinne hath bin committed with a ſtubborne hand, God hath puniſhed with deſtruction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Euen from hence muſt euery one confeſſe that he is a ſinner becauſe he carrieth a body ſubiect to corruption, and in time death ſhal ſeaſe vpon him. When as the Lord did ſee that the wickedneſſe of man was great vpon the earth before the flood, hee brought that deluge to ouer-flow the world, that the waters might breake the heart and ſtrength of the earth, that mens liues might be ſhortned by the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3231:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Elements, and ſo weakeneſſe bee brought vpon the world. We may ſee it by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Noe</hi> liued 950. yeares, <hi>Terah</hi> the father of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> liued but 205. yeares, and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> that was in a neere generation in the deſcending line from <hi>Terah,</hi> died at the age of an hundred and ten, in the 50. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> and the laſt verſe. So the yeares of men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the flood were ſtrangely altered, euer from 950. to 110. in ſome ſucceeding ages. Sinne is the cauſe of all this. Tyrants that rule enioy their kingdomes but a while as hiſtories can teſtifie. For becauſe their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and cruelties are moſt vntollerable, they are ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ended. And vngodly men they liue not out halfe their daies, the Lord hath ſaid it, and God perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it, when they are an impediment to his worke, &amp; when their iniquity cannot be endured, although it be not alwaies ſo. For he worketh diuerſly as he ſindeth occaſion: ſometime he ſmiteth, ſometimes he ſuffereth, his prouidence being not tied to any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits. But ſinne according to the nature of it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man to his end, and ſtill playeth the part of a deſtroyer. If this be ſo, let vs be carefull to auoide it, and carefull to amend it, make an end of ſinne before God make an end of you. For know this, where ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is: Gods hatred followeth, and will cut down that which diſpleaſeth him with a finall confuſion. Yet ſinne is of that nature that it deſires to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, the delight of it coueteth to bee euerlaſting, when a man is taken captiue and wonne to carnall bewitching pleaſure: he wiſheth to dwell there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing or interruption. How vnequall then is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3231:8"/>vice in the proceeding: for although it make an end of the ſinner, it will make no end of it ſelfe. Hence it is that repentance is deferred, and ſuffereth ſo many procraſtinations till a man finde a fitter time, a better inclination of his heart within, a more conuenient opportunity without, ſo making his tranſgreſſion to continue. Hence is it that the euill ſeruant ſaith, my maſter doth defer his comming, therefore he ſmites his fellow ſeruants and goeth on with a preſuming boldneſſe. And will not forecaſt his heauy euents, nor conſider, that although his maſter deferres his comming; yet he commeth after his deferring, and at laſt will end his enterpriſes with vnwelcome iſſues.</p>
                     <p>And to what purpoſe ſhal the world ſpinne out an vngodly third? when this fatall ſtroke ſhall cut it off: what fruite ſhall a man expect from a falling tree. Pleaſure and content beeing once changed become more ſorrowfull; euen as a mans ſorrow being chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged is ſo much more pleaſant. Alas this end is that which reacheth not ſinne alone, but for our ſinnes cuts off all that this earth can yeild. The principall matters of a mans eſtate, that he deſireth to get toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his ſoule to reſt on, by lawfull and good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, his end will cut him ſhort of a full fruition, and make his deſires lame in his greateſt purpoſes. This did <hi>Seuerus</hi> the Emperour truly ſee and finde by true experience, who hauing paſſed through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aduentures at laſt died in our land ouerladen with troubles weighing with himſelfe what his life had beene, he broke forth into theſe ſpeeches <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> — I haue beene all that might bee,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3231:8"/>and now am nothing the better. This end is that which ouerturneth all, and will giue a foule wound to the faireſt member of our earthly happineſſe.
<q>The ſecond is an end of perfection.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſo tempered his heauy blow with mercy, that the good ſhall gaine by the fall, that God which conſumeth others ſhall perfect them. And for this end the whole world may expect. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> the 21. The creature ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of corruption into the glorious liberty of the ſonnes of God. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and the other Apoſtles, not onely the creatures of the world, but we doe groane within our ſelues waiting for the adoption, to wit the redemption of our body. Here in earth the ſeruice of God is not abſolute, but in part, ioyned with many infirmities, the reward alſo of true obedience is not ſeene, ſo that the imperfection of things preſent ſeemeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a future accompliſhment. Here wee ſtand by faith, and our faith is wrought by hearing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God. Now although hearing of good newes be ſome comfort: and the reading of a letter doth ſomewhat reioyce the heart, that decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſtate of an abſent friend: yet theſe are not like the preſent fruition of the thing deſired. So when the Lord dealeth here by the ſacred <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the comfortable tidings of peace and ioy: Yet becauſe it is but in hearing, it ſeemeth to point out at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beyond, for the nature of words are only to ſignifie or to reſemble another thing beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, by repreſenting ſomewhat that lyeth hid. So
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3231:9"/>then if in this life our ſtate doth lie in hearing, to ſhew that we are farre of, neither yet attained to our full expectation. Our end ſhall be an end of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, to perfect that which before did want full perfection. Againe, hearing is for this life, ſeeing is for the next in enioying a happy and bleſſed viſion, a mans fight is the moſt noble ſence of the fiue, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that muſt be the guide or rather the inſtrument that is reſerued to conueigh the bleſſed gifts of the other life: that the things which are moſt perfect in themſelues, may be deriued to vs in the moſt perfect manner. Wherefore you ſee that becauſe our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion hath not all the fulneſſe that ſo worthy a cauſe requireth: Our end ſhall be an end of perfection, to finiſh thoſe hopes, and to make vp thoſe breaches that doe keepe vnder the minde, and doe here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrame it in ſome ſort.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, the vices of this world doe crie out for an end, that wickedneſſe may not vaunt it ſelfe, but that a better eſtate and a more perfect condition may beare the ſway. And indeede the vices of this world doe proclaime an end of perfection. For what infinite idolatry doth euen ſince the world ſtood, and at this very day ouer-ſpread the face of the whole earth? How doe baſe ſurfets and riotous exceſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound? How doe oathes breath forth without any reuerence or regard of him that is named? What op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and biting of poore men doth paſſe with haughtineſſe and pride? Can wee now thinke that the iuſt God can euer endure that theſe ſhould euer ſtand? Yea and flouriſh alſo, and out braue his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3231:9"/>No ſurely hee will bring matters to a better paſſe, and ſet things in a right order by a iuſt gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we muſt expect an end of perfection.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly and laſtly, as our religion doth require an accompliſhment, and as the vices of men that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt religion doe require a reformation, ſo our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues that doe not immediately concerne Gods worſhip, but are vſed as good meanes, and helpes for it, and the ordinary things that are either for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or for ornament of this life: they are here ſo full of want that they ſeeme to groane for a redreſſe, to be better ſeated by a happy end. Our knowledge and vnderſtanding, whereby we comprehend the deepe myſteries of God and the hidden qualities of his workes, is full of doubt and difficulty as we haue it in this life. <hi>Solomon</hi> that did wiſh it, and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his wiſh, yet heare how he cenſured it in the firſt of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and the laſt verſe. <hi>Much reading is a wearineſſe to the fleſh, and he that encreaſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge encreaſeth ſorrow.</hi> A mans ioy and mirth, which is of worldly bleſſings moſt principall, for men ſcrape all the reſt together to obtaine it, becauſe it is but a ſhadow, and a flying vanity as we haue it, heare how the ſame Author doth iudge of it who did enioy all things his heart could deſire. I ſaid of laughter thou art mad, and of mirth what is this that thou doſt, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the ſecond <hi>verſe</hi> the ſecond. To leaue the minde and come to the body, eating and drinking, the meanes to preſerue our naturall life, it is no priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge aboue the beaſt, therefore the baſeſt of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. When a certaine Poet that loued his eaſe, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3231:10"/>that content of pleaſing his belly, gaue <hi>Hadrian</hi> the Emperour a verſe, to this effect: the Emperour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man giuen to verſifying.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ego nolo Caeſareſſe,</l>
                        <l>Ambulare per Britannos, &amp;c.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>I would not be an Emperour <hi>to march among the Britans</hi> and to <hi>be nipt with the froſts of Scythia:</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour anſwered him in the like faſhion.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Ego nolo Florus eſſe,</l>
                        <l>Ambulare per tabernas, &amp;c.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I would not be Florus to walke from tauerne to tauerne, and to bury all my daies in the graue of ſwiniſh ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> So meane a thing is this corporall pleaſure to them that truly conceiue thereof. Let me leaue the minde, and the body, and view the outward contents that the earth affordes. The glory, the pride and honor of this life is much eclipſed with imperfection. That which is lift vp in one day, may fall downe the next. There is prepared a moth for appatell, and wormes and putrifaction doe waite for him that is aduanced: when this end ſhall come it plucketh the higheſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote, and layeth his honour in the duſt. Behold then wiſedome and content of minde, the pleaſure of the body, the outward pompe of worldly honour, being in themſelues lawfull if vſed with moderation, and directed to a right intent: Yet as we haue them in this life they ſuffer their diſeaſes. We muſt thinke of a time when they ſhall be perfected, and refined, for the God of nature doth order all things aright, and whereas they ſeeme heere to be kept in priſon or to miſcarry in diuers points, they ſhall be rectified
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3231:10"/>by an eſtate aboue, which doth fixe them vpon their true obiect.</p>
                     <p>Then ſhall wiſedome and knowledge receiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, we ſhall ſee the Lord as he is, not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely as in a glaſſe, but face to face as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
                     <p>Then ſhall a mans ioy be complete and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſeeing he ſhall enioy that is better then himſelfe: For earthly ioy is therefore imperfect, becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world is ſo excellent as a mans ſoule, and therefore it cannot reſt in theſe inferiour things, till it come to the Lord who is a ſpirit, euen the Father of ſpirits, in whom alone the ſpirituall ſoule doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſatisfaction. Then ſhall bodily ſuſtentation alſo ceaſe, the belly is here for meate, and meate for the belly, and God deſtroyeth both it and them: there ſhall be a feeding onely of the ſoule, and a drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that water, whereof hee that drinketh ſhall neuer thirſt as our Sauiour ſpeaketh. The ſpirituall contents are ſet downe by bodily deſcriptions. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the happineſſe is ſpirituall, for ſpirituall things are moſt excellent. Seeing all things muſt be moſt abſolute. <hi>Aquin</hi> and <hi>Lyra</hi> haue vrged this text a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turkes</hi> that dreame of carnall delights in a bodily paradiſe after death.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, that deſire of honour which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen men by nature, becauſe the earth is not able to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, doth point out the right way to wandring thoughts. A man ought to eſchew baſeneſſe, that is, to deteſt ſinne which doth worke a downefall, and to aſpire to that kingdome of glory: that here by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3231:11"/>honouring God, hereafter the Lord may honour vs, according to that ſpeech giuen out for our encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. <hi>To him that ouercommeth I will grant to ſit with me in my throne.</hi> In the third of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
                     <p>I haue here propounded two ends for you, an end of deſtruction, and an end of perſection. The firſt end is for all, the ſecond for a few. For vs let it be our care ſeeing we muſt end: let vs end the beſt waie: let vs not looſe that faire poſſibility wherewith God hath endowed vs, by taking vs from the multitude of ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, and made vs members of his Church, in as much as he ſheweth vs by his word what is to come: but let our life be ſo ſquared, that our conſciences may tell vs we ſeeke perfection. For woe be to him that endeth not the beſt way, and happie, yea thrice happie is hee whoſe end is the doore to happineſſe. Let that be our reſolution, which was the wiſh of an euill man, of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who hauing a little touch giuen him, and a certaine light of the end of Gods elect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a Prophet: brake out into a good deſire, let vs vſe it with a more ſound affection, that we may prooue more then wiſhers and woulders in the caſe. O that I may <hi>die the death of therighteous, and that my laſt end may be like his.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>So much of the end of the old world.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3231:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>I come now to the eſtabliſhing of a new.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When hee ſhall haue deliuered vp the kingdome to God the Father.</head>
                     <p>AS the king doth ſend forth his generall with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authoritie to the warre, who hauing ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the enemy, returneth in triumph, and all beeing finiſhed maketh a ſurrender of his place. So our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> came into the world from the Father with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall authority, here he diſcharged his office impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on him, and hauing confounded all his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, at the day of iudgement endeth the warre. And like a <hi>Dictatour</hi> that gouerneth only in times of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo the vſing his authority vpon rebellious men: When the worke is finiſhed, leaueth his function <hi>by deliuering the kingdome vp to the Father.</hi> Wee may ferch an expoſition to theſe words from the 28. <hi>verſe</hi> of this chapter. <hi>And when all things ſhall be ſubdued vnto him, then ſhall the Sonne alſo himſelfe be ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that put all things vnder him; that God may be all in all.</hi> Whereas the Lord did not viſibly gouerne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men by ſhewing the fulneſſe of his owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but gouerned it by men, keeping as yet his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty more ſecret: <hi>he ſhall then put downe all authority of men,</hi> and guide all things immediately by his owne hand. That is; <hi>To be all in all, to deliuer the kingdome to the Father, and to put downe all rule, all authoritie, and power.</hi> Becauſe of ſome obſcurity in theſe words, I muſt reſolue two doubts that ariſe from hence. Firſt of all: ſome may obiect, Wherefore is our Sauiour
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3231:12"/>ſaid to reſigne his kingdome to the Father? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Chriſts</hi> kingdome muſt haue no end. For the prophecy of him goeth to this purpoſe. <hi>Daniel</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 44. <hi>And in the daies of theſe kings, ſhall the King of heauen ſet vp a kingdome that ſhall neuer be deſtroyed, and the kingdome ſhall not be left to other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but it ſhall conſume and breake in peeces all theſe kingdomes, and it ſhall ſtand for euer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, <hi>Luke</hi> the 1, and the 33. the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Virgin Marie. He ſhall reigue ouer the houſe of</hi> lacob <hi>for euer, and of his kingdome there ſhall be no end.</hi> How then doth the Apoſtle ſay, hee ſhall bee made ſubiect, <hi>and deliuer vp the kingdome to the Father.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Arrians</hi> haue vrged this place againſt the diuinity of Chriſt, that he is not of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and equality with the Father, becauſe he is here ſaid to bee ſubiect and to giue ouer his kingdome, therefore his power and dignity is not eternall, hee that is God can be vnder none, as here the Sonnere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth his ſoueraignity to the Father. I will anſwer both theſe by expounding the words, for when they are well explained, theſe doubts will vaniſh of them ſelues: to this purpoſe I lay downe theſe two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, not withſtanding the words here ſeeme to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the contrary, Chriſt ſhall reigne for euer. For he ſitteth at the right hand of the Father, a place of honour and aduancement. If he then reigned before in the field, much more muſt he reigne in his owne pallace, where he ſitteth in the throne of Maieſtie. Chriſt is the head of the Church, if he be the head,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3231:12"/>then hee muſt needs gouerne ſtill, and keepe that height that is due to the higheſt part. His very hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity obteining honour aboue all creatures, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Angels themſelues, as it is in the firſt to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> prooued from my text. <hi>To which of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels did he ſay ſit at my right hand till I make thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thy foote-ſtoole.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond concluſion. In Scripture things that are heauenly are vſually aſcribed to the Father, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they appertaine to the Sonne if they doe not appertaine to his office, to diſcloſe to vs, and doe not concerne this life: then he puts them from himſelfe to the Father. Of this we haue ſundry examples. <hi>Our Sauiour Chriſt</hi> maketh himſelfe ignorant of the day of Iudgement. <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no man no not the Angels in heauen, nor the Sonne himſelfe ſaue only the Father.</hi> Some haue ſuppoſed that Chriſt as hee was man knew not that day, and certainely he knew it not by his humanity, although it is likely he knew it in his humanity. For as he was man, hee was king, and it derogateth from the Maieſty of a king to be ignorant in his owne times or affaires. Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> he had not the ſpirit by meaſure, therefore he knew all that a creature could know or receiue, by vertue of his vnion to the diuinity. But his meaning is, It is not a thing that appertaines to my office to declare, I came to teach things neceſſary to ſaluation, but this is a ſecret thing that muſt reſt in the counſell of my Father. So <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon the place, <hi>Non dubium eſt quin ad munus ſibi a patre impoſitum reſpiciat. He had reſpect to the commisſion that the Father had giuen him,</hi> when he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3231:13"/>ſaid he knew not the day of iudgement.</p>
                     <p>Againe <hi>Matthew</hi> the 20. <hi>verſe</hi> the 23. Chriſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the mother of the Sons of <hi>Zebedeus. To ſit at the right hand and left hand in my kingdome, is not mine to giue, but it is for them for whom it is prepared of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> No doubt but Chriſt had power to giue that as well as the Father.
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> For he ſaith in another place, <hi>all things are deliuered vnto me of my Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the meaning is, I come to teach patience, can you drinke of the cup that I muſt drinke of? and be baptized with the baptiſme that I muſt be baptized with? that is, my office now to declare, but to ſatisfie theſe climing thoughts, to tell who ſhall be higheſt or loweſt in the kingdome of God, and now at firſt, to anſwer your requeſt, I come not to doe it in this life: but my Father reſerueth it for whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in another world. Againe, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14. and the 28. <hi>The Father is greater then I.</hi> The <hi>Arrians</hi> haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed that place in the ſame manner, making Chriſt inferiour to the Father.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zanchius de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Elohim lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> But the meaning is. <hi>Status ille Coeleſtis apud patrem praeſtantior eſt iſto. The glory that I haue here is not ſo great as the glory of heauen.</hi> For when the diſciples were grieued becauſe he told them of his departure to the Father, he raiſeth them vp with this comfortable ſpeech. <hi>The Father is greater then I,</hi> that is, the heauenly comfort is better, then that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent you haue in my earthly preſence. From hence we may collect that the matters of heauen are by our <hi>Sauiour</hi> aſcribed to the Father, although they belong to him. Indeede the Father and the Sonne do reigne ioyntly togither, and whereſoeuer the one reigneth,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3231:13"/>the other reigneth alſo. But becauſe the Son tooke vpon him our fleſh, and was incarnate among men; whereas the Father was not made man, nor yet ſeene by any mortall eye, but reueileth himſelfe by the Son, as by his image. Earth is the kingdome of the Sonne, and heauen the kingdome of the Father. Theſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes call not the diuinity of the Father into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but all confeſſe him to be a king, yet he ſaith in the ſecond <hi>Pſalme</hi> and 6. <hi>verſe.</hi> I haue ſet my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vpon my holy hill of <hi>Sion.</hi> If Chriſts ruling do not exclude the ruling of the Father, by the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence the ruling of God the Father doth no way derogate from the dignity of the Sonne.</p>
                     <p>Theſe two concluſions being now ſet downe, all cauils againſt this truth doe vaniſh. For Chriſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is as large as euer. <hi>Euen when he giueth vp the kingdome to God the Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt is ſaid to deliuer vp the kingdome in three reſpects. Firſt, becauſe he ceaſeth to execute that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which neuertheleſſe he hath, as a Iudge that goeth from the bench, is a Iudge ſtill: although he giue no iudgement but imployeth his time in other occaſions. And as a warriour that liueth in the time of peace, or ſleepeth, doth retaine his old valour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he want opportunity to ſet forth his might by proouing it in outward action: So Chriſt is ſaid to reſigne his place, not that his authority is ſubiect to diminution, but that he maketh no ſhew, <hi>for when his enemies are all put vnder,</hi> there is no neede that any more blowes ſhould proceed from his kingly power.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3231:14"/>
                     <p>Secondly, Chriſt deliuereth vp the kingdome to God the Father, not becauſe his authority is impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but becauſe the manner of his kingdome ſhall be changed. He ſhall not reigne in the ſame faſhion, there needeth no preaching in heauen, becauſe there is no ſinne. There neede no ſacraments, for when wee enioy Chriſt that is the thing ſignified: wee ſhall want no outward ſignes. There neede no good lawes to keepe from ſtarting into wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereas the felicity of Saints is confirmed by an eternall decree. In this reſpect therefore hee giueth ouer the <hi>kingdome,</hi> becauſe hee chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the orders of this life into a new kinde of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
                     <p>The third and moſt abſolute expoſition is ſet downe by <hi>Aquin.</hi> Hee ceaſeth to increaſe his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. For here our <hi>Sauiour</hi> by the preaching of his word gaineth more ſoules to his kingdome, ſo ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his dominion further and further. But when the Lord ſhall haue made vp the number of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to his minde, then he will end the world and giue vp his kingdome, namely, hee will ceaſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his confines any more, but be content with the number of thoſe ſubiects that hee hath already. To end this point, we learne from hence how great his glory ſhall be, and how much it ought to draw our minds after it, Chriſt ſhall change theſe obſcure go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments on earth, into an abſolute fulneſſe, when he giueth ouer his fierce and ſtormy conqueſt, for the happy peace of a quiet calme. For here the moſt happie ſubiect that ſerueth the Lord, ſtandeth in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3231:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>field, and taketh on him the condition of a ſouldier. But when the tumults of this earthly warfare ſhall be appeaſed, when the Church Militant ſhall be made triumphant, when the Sonne ſhall end this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, infinite ſhall bee that conſolation, where the diuinity ſhall ſhine forth, and the Maieſty of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is declared. Let ambition refine it ſelfe and it ſhall climbe higher then yet it hath aymed by any politicke endeauour. For honour vpon earth is but a type or a ſhadow of that honour which is aboue. What ſtirring and ſhuffling haue we heare for high places? how obſequious will a man ſhew himſelfe, if that can promote him? what flattery of great men? ſometime onely for their aſſiſtance, or to be ſhrouded vnder their protection. Whereas all height is but lowneſſe, all glory but ignominie, and all maieſty but ſeruitude, compared to this ſupreame degree <hi>of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence.</hi> For the pooreſt <hi>Saint</hi> that is in <hi>Gods kingdome</hi> is in a greater ſtate of excellency, then was the royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Salomon,</hi> or <hi>Dauid,</hi> or the greateſt Monarch that euer the Sunne ſaw. For all theſe are but the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Sonne, and the Sonne tooke vpon him onely the forme of a ſeruant. And therefore he will end this kingdome becauſe it doth not ſure wel with his greatneſſe, neither thinketh he that it is worthy to continue, but lifteth vp his gouernment to that dignitie w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>h is like himſelfe. <hi>Hee will deliuer vp the kingdome to the Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>I come now to the third part, which is the forme of gouernment in this kingdome.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3231:15"/>
                     <head type="sub">Hee ſhall haue put downe all rule, and all authority and power.</head>
                     <p>I Finde three expoſitions of this place. Some an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Popiſh writers expound it of the Angels: God ſhall gouerne immediately by himſelfe, not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Angels in their degrees, as Miniſters to put his commands in execution as now they doe. <hi>Beza</hi> doth giue it a reſtraint to bad rulers vpon earth, God ſhall put them downe, and diſanull their authority, For in the next verſe it is ſaid. <hi>He muſt reigne till hee hath put all his enemies vnder feete. Calvin</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth good gouernours as well as bad, and indeede all gouernment in generall. The beſt way is to agree to him, and giue the words a large ſence. So when God ſhall come, he will not rule by ſubſtitutes or vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but he himſelfe will be all in all. Concerning the ſuperiority of the Angels, ſomething may bee ſaid, for the Apoſtles ſpeech may in a ſort be applyed to them. And the Schoolemen out of theſe words do diſpute the continuance of their dignity. But that which I conclude ſhall be in probability rather then exact demonſtration. Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> is commended for his ſilence, a fit patterne for my imitation. The ſtrange conceit wherewith <hi>Dionyſius</hi> hath poſſeſſed the Schoolemen of that <hi>Coeleſtiall Hierarchie,</hi> of three orders or companies of Angels one aboue another, and that in euery degree there are three rankes, ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3231:15"/>
                        <hi>Thrones,</hi> ſome <hi>Dominions,</hi> ſome <hi>Powers,</hi> ſome <hi>Angels,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dicunt qui poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, ſi tamen probare poſſunt quod dicunt, ego me iſta ignorare confiteor Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus in Enchir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id ad Laurent. cap.</hi> 58.</note> and ſome: <hi>Archangels, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe this inuention hath neither warrant in Scripture, nor force of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to confirme it, let it vaniſh of it ſelfe. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe, there are degrees among the Angels, ſome are higher, and ſome are lower. Wee reade of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> the <hi>Archangel</hi> that diſputed with the diuell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that Chriſt at the day of the reſurrection ſhall come with the voice of an <hi>Archangel.</hi> The Lord hath beautified the creation with varietie, one ſtarre differeth from another ſtarre in glory, In earth among men, one man hath greater gifts then another, among ſexes, the man is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the woman. Among liuing things, thoſe that haue ſence as the beaſts, exceede the trees, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing there is Order and difference. So likewiſe among the Angels. But whether it be by nature or by office, it is doubted. Perhaps by nature as in the reſt, perhaps their office is according to their nature, here I muſt confeſſe ignorance. A dignitie they haue whether it bee onely for a while according to the greatneſſe of their worke, or whether it continue longer. Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> is of opinion that their dignitie aboue one another ſhall be perpetuall, becauſe that earthly kings haue diuerſities of ſeruants in orders and degrees: much more the king of heauen, will haue ſeuerall ſorts of Attendants to adminiſter in that ſtate of glory. <hi>Zanchie</hi> confutes him from this text. If God doe aboliſh all power, if the Sonne ſeeme to end his kingdome in ſome ſort, then the dignitie that one Angell hath aboue another, muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3231:16"/>needs fall and Gods immediate power take place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Theſe arguments doe ſtand vpon likelihood, neither doe they command beleefe on either ſide. For reſolution; I dare with ſafety expound the words as of Chriſt, the Angels ſhall not gouerne then, as they gouerne now, ſome ouer one man, ſome for a citie, ſome ouer many, ſome in a larger, ſome in a ſmaller prouince, as God doth place them in their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to the greatneſſe of particular occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This kinde of ruling ſhall be ended togither with the end of the world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>That we may leaue the Angels.</head>
                     <p>Certainly theſe words may moſt properly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated to humane authority and ſecular gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We may likewiſe ſee the great wiſedome of the holy Ghoſt expreſſed by theſe three words, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, for herein we finde a moſt abſolute deſcription of earthly gouernment. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, rule doth ſignifie the height of place, or ſuperiority of a man in office. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Authoritie, doth import the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of rule, when it is not by vſurpation. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> betokeneth abilitie to diſcharge it. For then is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment happie, when theſe three are ioyned, a man to haue dignitie of rule, a lawfull authority, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſufficient to execute his function. Gods will is that gouernment ſhould bee well armed and furniſhed, that common wealths may enioy their priuiledges, and for his glorie to ſtand ſtoutly to their taske. And the miſeries of kingdomes doe then ſpring vp, when theſe are ſeuered. When a man ruleth by tyrannie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3231:16"/>inſteed of authoritie. When a mans authoritie is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered and ouerruled, that hee cannot ſmite as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth require. Or when hee hath both rule and authoritie wanting gifts or power to ſet them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. You ſee then theſe three doe rarely fit the purpoſe in deſcribing the condition of worldly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
                     <p>This dignitie is put downe at the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt for two reaſons. Firſt becauſe ſinne ceaſeth. For the law is not for the iuſt, but for their-religious, the diſobedient, and the ſinner. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. No happineſſe in religion or ſecurity in temporall matters can ſtand without it here on earth.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ. poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic.</hi> 1. <hi>ſee.</hi> 10.</note> 
                        <hi>M. Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> ſuppoſeth the worſt times of the world to haue beene before the flood. Wee may conclude it alſo from the greatneſſe of the plague a vniuerſall deluge. There were but eight iuſt men and a <hi>Cham</hi> among them, righteouſneſſe was ſo exceeding ſcant in that age. The cauſe of this by him is aſcribed the want of rulers, We reade not of any till the time of <hi>Nimrod</hi> the firſt Monarch, who liued after the flood. Law is the reſtraint, and the Magiſtrate the deſtroyer of ſin. From this we haue an vndeniable argument againſt the Anabaptiſts, abuſing that ſpeech in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of S. <hi>Mathew. The princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion: but he that will be chiefe among you let him be your ſeruant.</hi> Hereupon theſe men haue dreamed, that after Chriſts comming we ſhould bee without rulers or authoritie. See how this cauſe and this text doe combine to giue an ouerthrow to their fancie. Rule and authoritie, and power, muſt hold till the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3231:17"/>ſinnes of men bee ended vpon earth. And when is that? At the laſt day of iudgement, <hi>when the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is deliuered vp to God the Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, let vs quench a ſparke not yet broken out into that Anbaptiſticall flame, I meane our Noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts at home, that from the ſame words haue conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to breake the bond of Eccleſiaſticall <hi>iuriſdiction.</hi> The ſame way diſcouers their error. If our miniſtery be yet ſubiect vnto ſinne, and ſpecially to fall by erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous doctrine, there muſt be rulers to ſuppreſſe and cenſure it. If ſickeneſſe be here, here we muſt haue phiſicke, euen a moſt perfect rule, authoritie, and power, ſeeing the falles of religion are moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. For ſpirituall rulers are to cenſure things ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, to keepe vnder falſehood, and to curbe the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of faction. Onely where ſinne is not, there muſt gouernment ceaſe, when Chriſt ſhall wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way euery blemiſh in the life to come.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, in this life we are not growne to our full ripeneſſe, wee are in our none-age, nor as yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to the heritage of heauen. Now Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the fourth chapter to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> the firſt verſe. <hi>The heire as long as he is a childe differeth not from aſeruant, but is vnder Tutors and Gouernours till the time appointed of the Father. Status huius vitae asſimulatur pueritiae</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquin. The ſtate of this life is the ſtate of a childe,</hi> as long as we liue here, we muſt be guided, no man is ſo wiſe but hee wanteth admonition. The counſell of ſuperiours muſt direct vs, the counſell of Gods word muſt direct them, and both muſt ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Spirit of God to direct both. Euery one is of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3231:17"/>himſelfe vnſufficient to tread the ſteps of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, his care muſt be euer bent to chuſe a good lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that may guide his feete into the way of peace.</p>
                     <p>The next thing I obſerue from hence, is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of rulers in the changing of the world. The greatneſſe of their power is here declared. As the next life is gouerned by the Father, ſo the world ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be theirs and committed into their hands. There God is all in all, here on earth they are, all in all. And great is the ſtroke and infinite are thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that be carried in the name and office of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. The greatneſſe of their calling now muſt ſhew the greatneſſe of their charge. For God giueth not this honour for nothing, but as they ſtand for him in their dignity. So they be like him in their actions. Let this conſideration ſmite the heart of euery ruler, both ſpirituall, and temporall, ſeuerally to examine their conſcience, whether in their proceedings they make God a patterne. Euery one that is more then a priuate man, that hath either rule, or authority, or power, be it more or leſſe: it is a gift of God, and it is borne not for himſelfe, but for God. To the good is a reward vnſpeakeable, a double honour, for a double benefit. <hi>For wiſe men they ſhall ſhine like the brightneſſe of the firmament: but they that turnem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ny to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall ſhine like ſtarres in the</hi> 12. <hi>of Daniel.</hi> Seeing they liued here like ſtarres that did not keepe their light in their owne <hi>Sphaere,</hi> but diffuſed the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad vpon the earth: their glory ſhall bee like the ſtarres and anſwerable to their worke. Bleſſed then is that power in earth that beareth it ſelfe in true loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3231:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſubiection to the power in heauen. But to the bad I muſt denounce a true tragedy from this text. And indeede tragedies are for great men, the inſtitution is ancient, for in old time the Comedies were for the meaner ſort and we obſerue the ſame cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. If we may interpret that which is paſt, there is ſome terrible thing in this obſeruation. For the mighty to whome is giuen height of place and the ſame graced with a latitude of proſperity: they flie out without any feare; and becauſe they keepe not within compaſſe, they are wounded by a higher hand, and daſhed vnder the feete of a Supreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. The Lord will conteſt moſt ſharpely with theſe men in the day of iudgement that tooke the ſword from him, and either did not manage the cauſe with courage, or ſmote againſt him. He will complaine as <hi>Pompey</hi> did againſt the men he put in truſt.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Comment. de bello cibili lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>Caeſar</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, His often exclamations were bent againſt them. <hi>Aquo genere hominum victoriam ſpereſſet, ab eo initio fugae facto, pene proditus videretur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thoſe men whom he ſuppoſed would winne the victory, where the firſt that did turne their heeles to the enemy, and in a ſort be tray him. For vs and our times I now for beare to cenſure of actions, For in the matters of ſtate, that which is well done may haue an ill ſhew; and that which is ill done may ſeeme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable to ordinary apprehenſion. To come then to the conſcience where the teſtimony ſhould bee moſt infallible. It is a rule propounded by <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> and drawne from morrals of the Heathen (much more muſt it hold in the Chriſtian common
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3231:18"/>wealth (that the publike good muſt bee ſo preferred by the ruler, that hee ought to put it before the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate in his heart, the glory of God before his owne, and the welfare of the countrey before his priuate commodity, all the omitting of neceſſary good, all winking at euill doth lie vpon the necke of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour. This muſt excite a diligent care that a ruler muſt rule himſelfe with more then an ordinary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection. In theſe euill daies wherein the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall crie of ſinne betraies it ſelfe, when men cry out of a corrupt age, and ſay that the world is ending be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that vice abounds. Here you ſee a cauſe that requireth induſtry. The ſpirituall power muſt detect ſinne and inueigh with vehemency, the ſword of the temporall power muſt correct and reforme with ſeuerity, to procure amendment. I muſt confeſſe that we cannot haue <hi>Platoes</hi> common-wealth, neither can we ſo labour but our purging will leaue droſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind it. Sinne when it is ſmitten will riſe againe, and ſome abuſes will be incurable, yet a man muſt beſtir that power that he hath, and doe his beſt, or elſe God will puniſh him for ſlackneſſe, and viſite with a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy Iudgement becauſe he did not viſite offendours with his deriued authority, and that iudgement committed into the rulers power. That I may finiſh this point, there is a gouernment which maſters haue; and parents alſo ouer their children. For the Lord hath giuen much authority, power and rule to them. See the great care of almighty God, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to ſee things well ordered, and hath placed a threefold authority in the world, ſpirituall in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3231:19"/>paſtour, temporall in the Magiſtrate, as alſo domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call in priuate families in as much as a threefold cord is not eaſily broken. He in mercy ſtriueth to giue ſin the foyle and draw vnder the world into true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Doe maſters and fathers repreſent diuine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? Let them be then in Gods place, to bring vp and tutor thoſe vnder them in Gods feare, to teach and inſtruct them in religion, not to let them ſinke or ſwim, to let them liue or die in ignorance pretending buſineſſe, they haue no leaſure, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the diuell with a fooliſh baſhfulneſſe, that maketh them to let paſſe this duty. Doubtleſſe the Lord will require their blood at the hands of ſlacke ouerſeers. But when I ſay maſters muſt teach their ſeruants, I doe not meane, they muſt teach them to lie, or to deceiue, and by example, or command, to corrupt them in their youth in ſhewing thoſe baſe and falſe proceedings, that when the age is greene, and capable of all conditions, youth is ſpoyled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can diſcerne: and the new veſſell ſeaſoned with vnſeaſonable liquor, this is odious inſtruction. Is this to be a tutor or gouernour in Gods place. This is like to <hi>Antichriſt that ſitteth in the Temple of God, but aduanceth himſelfe againſt all that is called God.</hi> I haue the rather inſiſted vpon this ſubiect, for the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the earth, the power of hell will alwaies be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to poiſon the degrees of gouernment, and muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all the forces againſt true authority to hinder the endeauours of good men that they may be croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and oppoſed, that here the bond of amity may be broken, that the affaires of the world, may draw the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3231:19"/>minde another way, working like to <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that laid hold vpon the pillars whereon the houſe did ſtand, that ouerthrowing them: the houſe and the men might fall in a common ruine. If he alſo can lay hands on him that is commander, then he is in his prime, ſuch intentions that are foſtered in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places doe beſt agree with his deſires, and are moſt like to ſpread abroad, knowing that when the fumes and cloudes are fitted in the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re, when the sky is darke aboue, the ſtorme will come; and the earth ſhall feele a tempeſt.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, ſee that the Lord to ſhew his power, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs againſt them that are higheſt. To breake downe them that are already low, is an argument of leſſer might: but when theſe are brought downe whome none could tame, when their power is abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated that before was not to berſiſted by violence, or ſtubborn contradiction, or gain-ſaid in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: here we ſee a mighty arme, and a powerfull blow. This muſt bee a great argument to feare the Lord, and to dread his diſpleaſure, becauſe his reach is vnlimited, no compaſſe or ſtrength can ſtay his force. The greateſt man on earth oweth as much humility to God as the meaneſt, and is equally yoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to vndergoe the edicts of heauen. Wee preach alike to all, and God will deale without diſtinction. Chriſt in <hi>Daniel</hi> is deſcribed to ouerthrow king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. That Image which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſaw in the dreame with a gold on head, with armes and breſt of ſiluer, and the reſt: did either ſignifie the foure great Monarchies of the world or elſe the three firſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3231:20"/>with the remnant of <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſucceſſion. Although this Image was moſt glorious, yet a ſtone cut with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, brake the Image, and became a great mountaine, filling the whole earth. And as the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was not departed from Iuda, nor a Law-giuer from betweene his feete till <hi>Shilo</hi> came. So Chriſt will alwaies make his comming notable with alterations. When <hi>Shilo</hi> came firſt, <hi>Iuda</hi> loſt his Scepter, and when he commeth againe the world ſhall looſe all domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You ſee how infinite is the the power of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all earthly power. Let no man ſwell in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, although the Lord exalt him to height of dignitie, but that mildneſſe and moderation may temper him in all his counſels. For there is one aboue euery man, euen our Sauiour, that can turne him as he pleaſeth. The time ſhall come when ſcepters ſhall be broken, when power ſhall grow impotent, and when authoritie ſhall looſe her authoritie.</p>
                     <p>Thus much for the firſt, which is the <hi>doing of good,</hi> I will now enter into the ſecond which is the <hi>remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of euill. He muſt reigne till he hath put all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnder his fecte.</hi> Firſt of his <hi>kingdome:</hi> As Chriſt is God <hi>hee muſt reigne.</hi> Hee reigneth ouer all, as hee is Mediatour hee reigneth alſo Which office belongeth to him according to both his natures, whereby hee maketh his kingdome ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute by vniting two in one bond: reconciling the ſubiect and the ſoueraigne God and man. This aſſumed kingdome is the thing here mentioned, which is inferiour to the diuinitie. For Chriſt is God by nature, and of neceſſity, but he is Mediatour by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3231:20"/>and office: it was a thing arbitrarie, he might haue choſen whether hee would haue ſuffered the world to ſinke in ſinne, or to haue redeemed it by his merits. <hi>Ignatius</hi> therefore maketh a threefold diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, of all: firſt, of the creatures: ſecondly, of the office of the Mediatour aboue all creatures: thirdly, of the diuine nature. This kingdome hath a large extent, he reigneth euery way, and in euery place, in the rulers, and miniſters, one being the hand, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the mouth of Chriſt. In the world his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence extendeth to a falling ſparrow, and hee will iudge the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by the creatures, in the firſt to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> But two principall parts doe ſet out his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall regiment:</p>
                     <p>His word, which comprehendeth the <hi>lawes and ſtatutes</hi> by which his kingdome muſt be ordered: and the Sacraments, that are his oathe <hi>of allegiance</hi> to ſweare his ſubiects to fidelitie. I can not now ſtand vpon all: Onely I will inſtance is his word, for the ſame will make vs ſubiects, as beeing the chiefe triall of our obedience. For the word of God is the iudge and rule of euery word and deede. The chiefe rule a man hath within himſelfe is his conſcience; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the conſcience is, ſo is the man: a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will doe well, a large conſcience will ſwallow all, a ſcrupulous conſcience is troubleſome with nice curioſitie. Here may then appeare the ſupremacie of Gods word, that whereas the conſcience doth rule the man, Gods word doth rule and command the conſcience. For our waies are framed according to our minde: and our minde is framed by aduice.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3231:21"/>Chriſt hath ſo large a dominion in mens hearts that he ruleth the minds of the moſt vnruly, in the 110. Pſalme the ſecond verſe: <hi>Be the ruler in the middeſt of thine enemies.</hi> Hee will make the conſcience a mans executioner where it can not be a perſwader. When wicked men doe reiect God by their blaſphemous thoughts, or will doubt of the life to come, becauſe theſe ſpirituall things are inuiſible: yet there will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe a ſecret thought beyond that, which reacheth the Atheiſt, and maketh him to ſtoope and yeild a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. They that contemne or regard not the <hi>Lord,</hi> will giue teſtimonie in ſwearing by his name; to ſhew that he is the iudge of their ſpeeches, by him their aſſeuerations muſt win credit, ſo they confound themſelues. Euery Papiſt will pretend Chriſt, the Turkes ſpeake honourably of him. And the Gothes did ſpare the Chriſtians that fled to the temples for ſuccour when <hi>Rome</hi> was deſtroyed, a thing vnheard of in other places; for among Pagans they burnt and deſtroyed both Gods and temples, as S. <hi>Auſten</hi> obſerueth in the firſt booke <hi>De Ciuitate Dei</hi> and ſecond chapter.</p>
                     <p>Thus doth our Lord rule among his enemies; a moſt large power. Earthly Monarches bee their might neuer ſo boundleſſe, are kept within their owne precincts, and <hi>Illa ſe iactet in aula,</hi> is all they haue. Their power is confined to their owne <hi>terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories:</hi> but he who made all, ruleth all; and that man who is againſt him, he will make turne againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the ſting of conſcience. Let our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences therefore entertaine him peaceably, otherwiſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3231:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee will let looſe his maſtiue dogge to torment vs, when he ſeeth time. The conſcience of an euill man in this life, is like a dogge tyed vp, now it pulleth, and onely barketh. And as a dogge may bee ſtilled with words, or gifts, ſo worldly pleaſure, and merry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, will make quiet the troubleſome noiſe of an vrged conſcience. But when a man is looſed from the bonds of his fleſh, and ſeeth where hee ſtands: that which did barke before will bite then, and teare the hard and hardy ſinner. Alwaies therefore let vs honour and obey his word. We haue his kingdome in abundance. This place wherein we liue I may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call in this reſpect the <hi>Chamber of the King:</hi> ſuffer him therefore to win you, to ſubdue you by his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and proclamations in this place. Let this croſſe crucifie ſinne, that he may vanquiſh vnder his ſigne, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did <hi>Maxentius.</hi> It is written of him that going once to fight, a banner was ſeene in the ayre hauing a croſſe with this writing <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. In this thou ſhalt ouercome. So yeild your obedient hearts, that we may be victorious for our maſter, and not ſmite the ayre when we ſhould ſmite your ſinne: our endeauour we doe, but this victory is in the Lords hand. When I doe but conſider the many combates in this place, ſo much preaching againſt tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I can not but ſay, <hi>nihil ſupra,</hi> ſcarce can any thing be ſpoken that is not ſpoken, labourers haue beene ſo exquiſite, that a new ſpeaker may double at the firſt vpon what ſubiect his thoughts may faſten. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times here doe ſpring bitter hearbes to cure the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt diſeaſes, and to expell the ſpirituall peſtilences
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3231:22"/>out of this citie. Carrie not then ſo daintie ſtomacks, as to die in ſinne rather then take the potion, or like children, to leaue wormewood, and regard the tooth-ſomneſſe rather then wholeſomneſſe of the hearbe.</p>
                     <p>Here ariſeth a ſtarre to guide wiſe men to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, when the errours of Poperie and other falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods are confuted. Which light ſhould ſo guide the learner that the continuall diligent hearers might be furniſhed with abilitie to controll a Papiſt, or to foile an aduerſarie in an ordinarie point: if that <hi>Mammon,</hi> the pleaſures and diſtractions of this life, did not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe their hearts, that no man almoſt will goe beyond his profeſſion, but leaue learning for thoſe who teach it. Although in iudging and cenſures they flie quite out of compaſſe.</p>
                     <p>Here are adminiſtred words of comfort in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for weake mindes, to preuent deſpaire, in not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing common corruption. Bee not ſo hard as to ſcorne and neglect them, like the flint to ſend out the fire of reproch, in ſtead of hearts mollified with grace to receiue impreſſion.</p>
                     <p>Thus doe we endeauour that God might rule the beſt way, that you might yeild rather then ſtand out. But I feare we ſpeed as <hi>Pompey</hi> againſt <hi>Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates,</hi> who often did conquer him in the field: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he returned againe with a new armie, as if he had gained by the fall. In the like manner we are heard, and our ſayings paſſe for current. Yet whole ſwarmes and armies of offences doe continue. The Lord may complaine of hearing as he did with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the three and thirtie chapter of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3231:22"/>verſe 31. <hi>They ſay, come I pray you, and heare the word that commeth from the Lord, and they come vnto thee as the people vſeth to come, and my people ſit before thee, and heare thy words, but they will not doe them: for with their mouth they ſhew much loue, but their heart goeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their couetouſneſſe. And loe thou art vnto them as a louely ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice, and can play well vpon an inſtrument: for they heare thy words, but they doe them not.</hi> The verie faſhion of our times, men come to heare ſermons as they heare muſicke: to delight the eare, to ſee a mans skill, to paſſe their cenſure, and there is an end. Theſe humours muſt know this muſicke will raiſe vp a iarring ſound in the conſcience inſteed of a melodious harmonie: and will make them ſing a ſad note at their dying day. If Gods word bee a <hi>kingdome,</hi> it muſt worke vpon the heart. There it muſt ſubdue a rebell, and renew that part of the old man that lurketh in the boſome of the ſoundeſt hearer.</p>
                     <trailer>So much of the <hi>kingdome:</hi> I come to the <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> Firſt the <hi>Enemie,</hi> then the <hi>Ouerthrow.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>His enemies.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REctum eſt ſui iudex &amp; obliqui.</hi> A priuation is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and knowne by the habit: <hi>and an enemie</hi> by a <hi>friend,</hi> as a <hi>crooked line is well diſcerned if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with a ſtreight.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt then, a <hi>friend</hi> is diſcouered by his affection, if he loue and deſire ſocietie, if he take pleaſure in conuerſing with the partie: So if a man take delight
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3231:23"/>in holy exerciſes: that loue and reioycing is a token of a friendly diſpoſition. Whereupon we may iudge thoſe to be no friends, that cannot reliſh our praiers, to whom preaching is tedious: and ſuch heauenly matters grow troubleſome: Thoſe that care not to come to Church, but often keepe a way, becauſe they finde nothing agreeable to their minde: In as much as they care ſo little for Gods preſence in the publike aſſemblie, and regard comming to his houſe ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: they are no <hi>friends.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Geneſi. ad literam lib.</hi> 11, <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> a true <hi>friend</hi> is tried in aduerſitie, ſo muſt wee ſtand in temptation. For God will ſifte and ſearch the ſtabilitie of our loue. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> thinketh it had beene no great matter of commendation for <hi>Adam</hi> to ſtand in Paradiſe, if none had tempted him to fall. If he had beaten backe the alluring temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lord might well haue crowned him with the rewards of bleſſedneſſe. The caſe is euery mans owne, the Lord will command to come to him, and caſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments in the way to draw from him, that he may trie, whether we wil chuſe. Yea as the diuel at the firſt entered into the Serpent, the moſt ſubtile of the beaſts of the field: ſo he will euer contriue his ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems in the wiſeſt manner. God hath ſaid, he would ſet enmitie betweene the Serpent and the womans ſeede, and he will euer be biting at the heele, if hee cannot reach the head. Here wee condemne them for no friends, that will ſhrinke at euery ſtorme, men that are well diſpoſed in themſelues: but will bee wrought into euery ſhape, and drawne any whither by perſwaſion. That ſee not the plots laid againſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3231:23"/>them, but take all that is offered; running through thicke and thin without difference, ſo they may not diſpleaſe themſelues or others.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, true <hi>friendſhip</hi> is conſtant, And as God loueth to the end, ſo muſt his <hi>friends</hi> be led by the ſame perſeuerance. From hence we condemne the <hi>Arminian friendſhip</hi> that ſtarteth aſide like a broken bow. They imagine a man may haue the Spirit of God, the graces of regeneration, and bee partaker of the priuiledges of a Saint., yet fall away and bee damned. Theſe men haue deuiſed ſuch a worſhip towards God, as olde <hi>Bias</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> brought in <hi>friendſhip</hi> towards men. When he had conſidered mans fickle diſpoſition, hee gaue counſell, his loue ſhould not be too earneſt, but ſo to loue that he may thinke of a time to hate. If friendſhip may be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act that it will bee euer: and him that breaketh off we cenſure an hypocrite, or a wauerer, or that hee conceiued vaine flaſhes of vnſetled loue: ſo he that prooueth an Apoſtate, was neuer a Saint: either he was an hypocrite, or had ſome good naturall deſires in ſpirituall things, but neuer well ſeated by the grace of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, true <hi>friendſhip</hi> excludeth all <hi>Neutrals</hi> and <hi>Corriuals,</hi> being onely among two according to <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> For if our fountaine of loue ſhould runne out through many channels, it would bee emptie. Therefore hee who is all complementall, and will loue euery bodie, doth indeede loue no bodie. I confeſſe the loue of charitie is due to all, but the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue affection that is placed on a friend, cannot
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3231:24"/>be well diſperſed among multitudes. So the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is with God. Wee muſt giue a certaine loue to the creatures, but there is a loue due to God, that no creature muſt haue beſides. Our Sauiour hath ſaid, <hi>No man can ſerue two maſters:
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Math.</hi> 6.24.</note> for either he will loue the one and hate the other, or leane to the one, and deſpiſe the other: ye cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Likewiſe in the 12. of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> verſe 30. he diſclaimeth all <hi>Neutrals</hi> that would giue way to the Phariſies againſt him, and notwithſtanding did wiſh him well in heart. <hi>He that is not with me, is against me: and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth abroad.</hi> Therefore commit not euill, and accuſe the times. Breake not Gods law, and accuſe prouocation. This is to play with both hands, if ye wil be friends, keepe to God alone, reſiſt euill prouocations, ſtand againſt euill cuſtomes, and reforme them.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto I haue deſcribed a <hi>friend,</hi> that I might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare an enemie. For although <hi>friendſhip</hi> be a humane vertue, yet in the way of ſimilitude it doth in ſome points excellently expreſſe our dutie to God: and ſo he vouchſafed the name of a <hi>friend to Abraham.</hi> Now muſt I paſſe this dreadfull ſentence, He that in ſome meaſure is not ſuch a <hi>friend</hi> is an <hi>enemie.</hi> If we could deuiſe a middle betweene both, all would flocke thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Men would for their own turne giue God ſome ſeruice, except where his law is tedious and difficult; in thoſe parts they would pleaſe themſelues, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an excuſe, becauſe of the infirmities of fleſh and blood. If we could open this <hi>middle ſtate,</hi> it would be the moſt welcome and plauſible doctrine that euer
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3231:24"/>the world heard. But this cannot be. Our religion maketh no <hi>veniall ſinnes</hi> here, it promiſeth no <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie</hi> hereafter. There a man ſhall finde a heauen or a hell, here he muſt finde himſelfe a <hi>friend</hi> or a <hi>foe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The enemies of God are of two ſorts, either open or ſecret. The open enemies are of three ſorts, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, the Iewes and the Turkes, Although there bee ſome doubt concerning the laſt, whether they be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or ſecret, ſeeing they ſpeake well of our Sauiour and acknowledge the Bible, he being an Arrian that togither with Neſtorian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Munke did make their <hi>Alcoran.</hi> Yet I agree to Tilenus in his tractate <hi>de aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Chriſtihoſtibus,</hi> who placeth him among the open enemies, becauſe hee doth perſecute the Chriſtian name, whereas the Heretikes doe grace their errours by Chriſts name, and pretend his authoritie. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret enemies againe are of three ſorts, either here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, or profaners, or hypocrites, which are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his houſhold. I doe but repeate theſe diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, my intent only is to take the office of a <hi>Scoute</hi> or <hi>Sentinell</hi> to diſcouer this hoſte of aduerſaries, and leaue them for others to aſſault: and for a ſtronger arme to cloſe with in the field. But leſt I ſhould by the diſcouerie of ſo huge an armie, ſeeme to worke the ſame effect that the Spies did when they returned from the land of Canaan. They terrified the people by relations of ſo mighty giants, and the ſonnes of <hi>Anak</hi> that the men had no courage but their heart melted with aſtoniſhment: I ſhall avoide this by the next point, there we ſhall ſee ſee them ſtrongly ſubdued by a fearefull fall, theſe <hi>enemies ſhall be put vnder feete.</hi>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3231:25"/>
                        <q>Their ouerthrow, vnder feete.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>This heauie lot did the Heathen imagine due to the Giants for oppoſing their Gods.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Famaeſt Enceladi ſemiuſtum fulmine corpus</l>
                        <l>Vrgeri mole hac In Virgil.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Aetna was thought a burden weighing downe one of this companie. In Scripture this is taken as a note of conqueſt as <hi>Ioſua</hi> 10.24. <hi>The captaines of the people did tread vpon the neckes of the fiue Kings.</hi> Which thing no doubt was a type of this, as <hi>Ioſua</hi> that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Sauiour was of the eternall Sauiour <hi>Ieſus.</hi> In this kinde alſo <hi>Ioas</hi> derideth <hi>Amazia King of Iuda.</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.18. ſhewing his weakeneſſe and arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnder this ſimilitude, <hi>The thiſtle</hi> that was in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon <hi>ſent to the Caedar</hi> that was in Lebanon, ſaying, <hi>Giue thy daughter to my ſonne to wife, and a wilde beaſt came and trode downe the thiſtle.</hi> For all the enemies of God doe fall miſerably, finally, and in the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned manner, and the extremities of all ruine ſhall confound him that is not an embracer of religion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Obſerue two things in this puniſhment <hi>torment</hi> and <hi>ſhame.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Torment.</hi> As a man that is preſſed to death, doth groane and languiſh vnder the weight, without the comfort of a little eaſe, or a breathing time to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength, to vndergoe the torture with any pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: ſo are the eternall woes of another life. Gods anger and heauy iudgement ſhall weigh downe the ſinner, the burden of his diſpleaſure vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall be intollerable, and inſupportable, griefe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3231:25"/>ſhall make the ſinner to ſinke vnder the heauineſſe. This did he a little ſee that cried mine iniquities are gone ouer my head, and are a burden to heauy for me to beare, yet this is the voice of repentance and not of deſperation. So heauy a loade is a mans offence when it preſſeth vpon the conſcience.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 <hi>Baſeneſſe</hi> and ſhame maketh vp the <hi>miſery.</hi> As he that lieth vnder foote is in the ſtate of <hi>ignominie</hi> and reproch: So at the day of iudgement when a mans villanies are laid open, when his Maieſtie appeareth who was offended, then a man ſhall haue his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe truely ſeene like <hi>Adam</hi> in Gods preſence. That which before he did glory in, ſhall then make him to hide himſelfe if it weare in his power: where the filthineſſe of ſinne ſhall be laide open in true colours. And are theſe the men that muſt not now be ſpoken to: and ſtrout it in their gallantry? Their wit in this deſerueth commendation, that they honour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and in a caſe of neceſſitie doe magnifie their practiſes, very neede requireth it, they muſt a little braue it now, they fall ſo low hereafter. The pretious pearle of the word is ouer topped by the haughtie, and now ſet light by, and the labours of preaching are as a thing trampled vnder by theſe men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe two muſt change places, God muſt haue the glory, and they the ſhame. For wherefore is it that theſe flouriſhing offenders are hearers of it, for the learning or the eloquence, or ſome worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Whereas ſaluation is built vpon ſimple admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and common principles, things that make no ſhew: becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> would bring downe all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3231:26"/>mane inuention and pride to this plainneſſe. All brauery, policy, learning, elocution, muſt at that time ſtoope to this ſimplicitie of diuine truth: whereas now we can ſcarce get this inward ſubſtance, this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of diuinitie to take place, but theſe outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornaments doe obſcure it. Strange and lamentable is the folly of the world. As men that are vnfurniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed come to a tree to gather fruite, and when they are come: they onely looke vpon the faire body of the tree, and the goodly bowes, and if they can ſnatch a branch they runne away, and leaue the fruite behind: So fareth it with our common auditours, They are ſicke and want, yet come to get ſome new thing to pleaſe their fancy, that may tickle the care, or delight the minde: returning with empty ſoules, as if God had ordained his word to pleaſe and not to profit. Let this then haue the preheminence now, leſt the contempt of ſo high a thing lay the auditour in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour.</p>
                     <p>Conceiue now what it is to lie vnder the feete of God. They ſhall call for mountaines to couer them, the weight of iudgement ſhall be ſo heauy. Worldly ſorrow is grieuous to fleſh and blood, burning in fire is a torment that cannot be endured: this is a Tophet prepared with much wood, and the breath of the Lord as a riuer of brimſtone to kindle it. Trauell of women is a plague in earth for ſinne, this ſuddaine deſtruction that commeth vnawares is like it. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. Diſcontents of this life doe ſometimes preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt humane infirmitie, that a man ouerwhelmed will delect his minde, goe againſt nature, and lay
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3231:26"/>violent hands vpon himſelfe, If this be ſo in the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes on earth; how ſhall it fare with the ſorrowes of hell? If a man doe thus ſhrinke when he is ſmitten by the hand of the creature? how ſhall he ſinke when he lieth vnder the foote of the Creator? See here in this life how a wounded conſcience doth diſmay a perplexed ſoule. It maketh a man forget all worldly pleaſure, that cannot helpe him: It ouercommeth all earthly ſorrow, for that yeildeth vnto this: neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, a troubled minde hath ſome hope, God may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe out of that agonie. It ſeeth not God and his iudgements, but feareth and ſuſpecteth a miſerie to come; it beholdeth vengeance a farre of. If that may ſo lay a man vnder foote in his life, how ſhall the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eternall puniſhments ouerthrow him. What ſhall I ſay more.</p>
                     <q>Pugna ſuum finem cumiacet hoſtis habet.</q>
                     <p>Equity <hi>requireth the fight ſhould ceaſe when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is vnder foote.</hi> I neede to threaten no longer. But that my end may giue a direction to the end of others. Beware this ditch, for ſake ſinne that maketh an enemy to God, let his word ſmite your conſcience by reforming you, I cannot ſpeake it without griefe, nor (I thinke) you heare it without pittie, that our Church ſhould haue thoſe hearers that are diligent, and yet vnſound in practiſe, ſome that ſet their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion light, let it goe either way, that follow the world and trouble not their braines about heauen. Theſe men are to bee put among the enemies, among the Iewes and Turkes, euen thoſe that haue not knowne God, that haue blaſphemed Chriſt, that haue borne
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3231:27"/>armes againſt him: They are in the ſame degree with them, all are ſtickes to be put in the ſame bundle, and caſt into the ſame fire. The diuell hath hid this ditch into which they fall, their owne luſt hath beene a miſt that roſe into the eies to darken their ſoule: that they will not beleeue it, till they feele it: nor beware it, till they finde it. Yet make peace, for you fight with the Lord of hoſts, you ſhall be ouermatched at the laſt: although you ſee not his vengeance at the firſt. Be hot then in his cauſe, ſtand for him like a friend, or elſe he will account you as his foe, worſhip him here with a conſtant and faithfull heart, fall downe before his feete by praier and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance leſt you fall vnder his feete in the day of wrath.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3231:27"/>
                  <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED IN PAVLES CHVRCH VPON SAINT <hi>Steuens</hi> day. 1618.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ACTS, 7.57, and 58.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Then they gaue a ſhoute with a loude voice, and ſtopped their eares, and ranne vpon him all at once.</p>
                        <p>And caſt him out of the citty, and ſtoned him.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Steuens Day.</hi> The <hi>Day</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth me to my <hi>Text:</hi> the <hi>Day</hi> of S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> and the <hi>Text</hi> of S. <hi>Steuen.</hi> But how concerneth it Saint <hi>Steuen?</hi> Declareth it his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, his <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>comming into</hi> the world? like the day before this, or his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, his <hi>Death and going out</hi> of the world? like the day after to morrow. His <hi>Death,</hi> certainely and neceſſarily. Yeſterday was the <hi>Birth</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this day the <hi>Death</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> both compriſing the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Chriſtianitie:</hi> That day teaching vs to <hi>liue,</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3231:28"/>this day teaching vs to <hi>die:</hi> or rather <hi>both</hi> teaching vs to doe <hi>both,</hi> both to <hi>liue</hi> and <hi>die.</hi> For our meeting: the <hi>Day</hi> of S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> leadeth vs to the <hi>Text</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> and the <hi>Text</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen:</hi> to the <hi>Death</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen.</hi> The <hi>end</hi> of this <hi>ſtory</hi> is the <hi>ſtory</hi> of his <hi>end:</hi> and thus much for the <hi>contents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>contents</hi> of my text being <hi>Death—Perſecution,</hi> the parts thereof ſhall be anſwerable; two, the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters,</hi> and the <hi>Perſecuted:</hi> the firſt pointing at a <hi>pluralitie</hi> of <hi>Iewes,</hi> the ſecond at a <hi>ſingular Chriſtian:</hi> firſt of <hi>them,</hi> then <hi>of Him:</hi> ſo I direct my diſcourſe <hi>In them,</hi> the <hi>Perſecuters,</hi> we may note the very <hi>body</hi> of <hi>perſecution:</hi> they did aſſault him <hi>fine waies,</hi> (if ye will) with <hi>fiue members: ore, aure, corde,</hi> and (as our phraſe is) <hi>manibus, pedibuſque:</hi> they did ſet vpon him with their <hi>mouthes, eares, hearts, feete,</hi> and <hi>hands.</hi> Firſt with their <hi>mouthes, then they gaue a ſhoute with a loude voice.</hi> Secondly, with their <hi>eare, &amp; ſtopped their eares.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with their <hi>hearts,</hi> they did it <hi>all at once.</hi> Fourthly, with their <hi>feete,</hi> they <hi>ranne vpon him.</hi> Fifthly, with their <hi>hands, they caſt him out, and ſtoned him.</hi> In <hi>him,</hi> the <hi>Perſecuted,</hi> two things onely are propounded: the <hi>Place,</hi> and the <hi>Perſon:</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> was <hi>without the citty,</hi> and the <hi>Perſon</hi> S. <hi>Stenen.</hi> Arguing his <hi>thrice</hi> noble excellence, he is <hi>thrice</hi> repeated, <hi>they ranne vpon him, they caſt out Him, and they ſtoned Him.</hi> Yee conceiue the ground of my diſcourſe concerning <hi>his</hi> laſt houre, which Chriſt grant that we may remember to <hi>our</hi> laſt houre.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In generall,</hi> obſerue this <hi>from the generals: Many Perſecuters</hi> knit themſelues together againſt <hi>one,</hi> or a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3231:28"/>
                     <hi>few Perſecuted: a kennell of Dogges</hi> ſingle out <hi>one Deere:</hi> and we heare <hi>them,</hi> hunting after <hi>Him</hi> in my text. <hi>Saul Doeg,</hi> the <hi>Ziphims</hi> and the <hi>Amalekites</hi> againſt <hi>Dauid: Pontius Pilate, Herod, and his men of warre</hi> againſt the <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>Dauid:</hi> the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies,</hi> againſt the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> againſt <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> In our <hi>time,</hi> the <hi>Turkes, Iewes, Mahometanes,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> In our <hi>parts,</hi> the <hi>Catholikes</hi> (as they call themſelues) againſt the <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> And in our <hi>land,</hi> againſt our <hi>few—poore Miniſters—</hi> It is the <hi>Day</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> I will ſpeake the <hi>words</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> and I hope with the <hi>heart</hi> of S <hi>Steuen —Lord lay not this ſinne to their charge.</hi> Act. 7.60.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of the fiue particulars,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is how they aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted S. <hi>Steuen</hi> with their <hi>mouthes;</hi> as we phraſe it, they <hi>ranne vpon him with open mouth,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they <hi>ſhouted with a lowde voice,</hi> ſaith my text.</p>
                  <p>A rare propertie of <hi>Perſecuters,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                     </label> to make their <hi>tongues</hi> the inſtruments of <hi>Perſecution.</hi> The text te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtifieth that theſe were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that their <hi>words</hi> were <hi>ſwords,</hi> and that their <hi>ſhoute</hi> was the <hi>prologue</hi> to their <hi>tragedie.</hi> So <hi>Act.</hi> 19.32. the <hi>Epheſians</hi> made a <hi>confuſed out-cry, to cry out</hi> for the diſciples <hi>confuſion.</hi> Peſtilently, politicke: that the <hi>opening</hi> of their <hi>mouths,</hi> might <hi>ſhut</hi> their <hi>eares</hi> from conueying compaſſion to the <hi>heart,</hi> by hearing the paſſion of the <hi>Perſecuted.</hi> As ſouldiers beate the drumme, to bury the groanes of their dying troopes: and the Idolatrous Iewes ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choed out the ſound of their ſhrill inſtruments, to drowne the ſhreekes of their frying children, forced through the fire to <hi>Molech:</hi> Thus they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3231:29"/>
                     <hi>they ſhouted with a loude voice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Surely theſe Iewes haue ſome of their <hi>off-ſpring:</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">appl. </seg>
                     </label> yet ſuruiuing <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> crying and yelling againſt the <hi>Perſecuted.</hi> Euen the ſanctified the <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> did euer the <hi>Moone</hi> behold the like <hi>barking</hi> rhetoricke, as hath beene yelpd out againſt our <hi>Prince</hi> and people, by <hi>Becanus, Tortus, Eudaemon, Lesſius</hi> and <hi>Scioppius</hi> yea and <hi>Suarez</hi> alſo. Adde our owne <hi>anominals,</hi> our Engliſh popiſh pamphlets: and finally 39. barrels of gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder ſhould haue made vp the <hi>full cry, of thoſe foule Hell-hounds.</hi> They thought to haue made vs <hi>all Steuens, all Martyrs,</hi> to haue deuoured vs <hi>all,</hi> when they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, when they had ſo <hi>opened</hi> their <hi>mouthes</hi> againſt vs. But <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>rumpatur quiſquis, rumpitur invidia.</hi> Let them throate out their malice againſt vs <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>with a loude voice,</hi> till they rend their <hi>mouthes</hi> to their <hi>nables.</hi> We hope that the <hi>hand</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> will alway defend vs from the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Perſecuter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next as they did <hi>open</hi> their <hi>mouthes</hi> againſt the <hi>eares</hi> of Saint <hi>Steuen:</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſo here they did <hi>ſtoppe</hi> their <hi>eares</hi> againſt the <hi>mouth</hi> of S. <hi>Steuen.</hi> As the <hi>Muſh-rome</hi> is <hi>all Head,</hi> ſo they were <hi>all mouth:</hi> they would <hi>ſpeake all</hi> but <hi>heare nothing:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they did <hi>ſtoppe their eares</hi> ſaith my text.</p>
                  <p>But conſider the cauſe of this their <hi>obturation,</hi> and <hi>obduration:</hi> S. <hi>Steuen</hi> did <hi>goade</hi> them vp with a <hi>ſharpe ſermon,</hi> and the vild <hi>Beaſts</hi> could not but <hi>Kicke</hi> at him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 51. he tearmed them <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a ſtiffenecked people of deafe <hi>eares,</hi> and dull <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 52. hee told them plainely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3231:29"/>that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, murderers and traiters. His rough reprehenſion <hi>through</hi> their <hi>eares,</hi> woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their rebellious <hi>hearts:</hi> (as a reſolute ſouldier will ſometime fetch of one of the garriſon through their owne <hi>loope-hooles.) Therefore,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they did <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, make their <hi>eares</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they did damme vp euery <hi>chinke and creuiſe,</hi> that the report of the leaſt ſyllable might not enter into their ſtubborne <hi>hearts:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they did <hi>ſtoppe their eares</hi> ſaith the text.</p>
                  <p>An vndoubted truth:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>Reprooue a Sinner</hi> and thou doeſt <hi>raiſe a Perſecuter.</hi> S. <hi>Steuen preached</hi> againſt them, inſtantly they <hi>ſtopped their eares and ranne vpon him. Chriſt taught it, Math.</hi> 7.6. If thou giue holy things vnto <hi>dogges,</hi> they will turne againe and <hi>teare</hi> you. <hi>Chriſt felt it, Luk.</hi> 4.28, and 29. Chriſt made an <hi>excellent ſermon</hi> to his <hi>owne countrymen,</hi> and his owne <hi>country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> would haue plunged him from the pitch of a ſteepe mountaine for his <hi>excellent ſermon.</hi> And eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian knoweth it: Let thy reprehenſion <hi>wound</hi> the wicked man, <hi>&amp; aeternum ſeruat ſub pectore vulnus,</hi> the <hi>Adder,</hi> will <hi>ſtoppe his eares,</hi> but <hi>ſting mortally. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah</hi> ſhall looſe his <hi>liberty,</hi> if he teach <hi>Ahab: Iohn Baptiſt</hi> his <hi>head,</hi> if he touch <hi>Herodias:</hi> and S. <hi>Steuen</hi> his <hi>life</hi> if he <hi>rebuke</hi> the <hi>Iewes:</hi> Vpon his <hi>reproofe</hi> they <hi>ſtoppe</hi> their <hi>eares,</hi> and what followes, remaineth to be expreſſed in the point following.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Deſpiſe not propheſying:</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of hearing ſermons. If ye come to <hi>heare</hi> the preachers, as the <hi>rich</hi> phariſies did. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.14. <hi>to mocke them:</hi> or as the <hi>learned</hi> phariſies did, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.15. to <hi>intrap</hi> them: know ye are within a <hi>degree</hi> (of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3231:30"/>impietie) of thoſe <hi>dogges</hi> which will <hi>teare</hi> their <hi>teachers,</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſerpents</hi> which will <hi>ſting</hi> their <hi>char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> of theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> who did <hi>ſtoppe</hi> their <hi>eares,</hi> and did <hi>ſtone</hi> their <hi>Preacher.</hi> Nor may yee thinke to feed the poore preachers, as the <hi>thiefe</hi> doth the dogge, <hi>porrigit panem vt ſileat,</hi> he giueth him <hi>bread</hi> that he may not <hi>barke:</hi> the <hi>Beneuolence</hi> muſt not tonguetie the truth, but we muſt pleade Gods cauſe though it be againſt our <hi>Benefactours.</hi> Much leſſe may yee dreame that we will <hi>preach</hi> to you, as the <hi>Kite</hi> craued his damme to <hi>pray</hi> for her, <hi>cum toties aras dei rapinis violatis: when wee ſee the theefe wee muſt not runne with him,</hi> and (by our ſilence) we muſt not <hi>bee partaker with the Church-robber.</hi> We muſt practiſe with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did pray for, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.20. not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> alſo: Wee muſt ſpeake <hi>truly,</hi>—yea and <hi>bouldly</hi> alſo: and we hope ye will not <hi>ſtoppe your eares againſt vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To returne to theſe <hi>Perſecuters:</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that wee ſhould not thinke that they did <hi>open</hi> their <hi>mouthes</hi> ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or <hi>ſtoppe</hi> their <hi>eares</hi> vnaduiſedly, it followeth how their <hi>hearts</hi> tutored them in this leſſon of blood: <hi>they ranne vpon him all at once:</hi> ſo wee tranſlate it: the greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Beza</hi> readeth it, <hi>concorditer with one heart,</hi> and the old tranſlation, <hi>Vnanimiter with one minde.</hi> The originall is very ſignificant, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in one place,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> with <hi>one minde.</hi> Deriue it from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, according to the double ſignification thereof, both <hi>animus</hi> the minde, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>anger:</hi> and then it implyeth <hi>one anger</hi> flaming from <hi>one ſrule,</hi> enough to <hi>animate</hi> there inraged fury. The phraſe of <hi>friends</hi> is more then verified, in S. <hi>Steuens foes:</hi> of thoſe we do
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3231:30"/>ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that there is <hi>one ſoule in two bodies:</hi> of theſe we may ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> that there was <hi>one ſoule</hi> in a thouſand bodies. <hi>They ranne vpon him <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> with one minde, all at once</hi> ſaith my text: or with <hi>one accord</hi> as we reade it in our latter and better tranſlation. Note:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                     </label> The wicked will be at <hi>Vnitie</hi> to perſecute the <hi>good:</hi> theſe Iewes, how they <hi>ranne <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> all at once</hi> vpon S. <hi>Steuen?</hi> as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>all</hi> as <hi>one</hi> man ran vpon him: and as <hi>Ignatius Epiſt.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they <hi>all harped vpon one ſtring. Pſal.</hi> 2.2. the Princes did <hi>band</hi> themſelues againſt the Lord and againſt his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.24. <hi>Zidkiiah</hi> and foure hundred falſe proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts <hi>accorded</hi> againſt <hi>Michaiah,</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.43. the <hi>Lagidae</hi> and <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eucidae,</hi> they <hi>mingled themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lues with the ſeede of men,</hi> they <hi>married,</hi> to <hi>Vnite</hi> their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the poore people of <hi>Iudae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Heretickes</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord againſt the <hi>Orthod xe:</hi> there hath beene many a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, many a <hi>Theeuiſh conuentic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> againſt the truth ſay our Church-ſtories: onely that of <hi>Trent</hi> was none of them. <hi>Theeues</hi> compacting againſt <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men,</hi> haue <hi>Vnitie: Cyprian Epiſt.</hi> 69. and the <hi>Turkes</hi> combining againſt <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> haue their ſingular <hi>Vnanimitie,</hi> they terme themſelues <hi>Iſlami,</hi> that is, <hi>men of one minde,</hi> iuſt, the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of my text. This muſt bee ſo: For the diuell will <hi>attone</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to doe a greater miſchiefe. Like <hi>Sampſon</hi> hee will tie his <hi>Foxes</hi> by the <hi>Tailes,</hi> to <hi>ſet fire</hi> where they goe. So <hi>agreed</hi> theſe <hi>woolues to worry</hi> this innocent <hi>lambe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: They ranne all at once vpon</hi> S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> to <hi>martyr</hi> him, to <hi>murder</hi> him.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3231:31"/>
                  <p>Let vs (as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <hi>Goliah</hi>) mite them with their owne <hi>ſwords:</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> as <hi>Iulian</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſtudying Philoſophie: let vs <hi>propriis pennis percellere,</hi> ſhoote them through with their owne <hi>Shaftes:</hi> If they ranne <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, at <hi>once</hi> againſt vs, let vs <hi>ſtand</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>one</hi> againſt them. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.9. Let vs bee <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Friends</hi> alone, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Brethen</hi> alone, but both: let vs be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Friendly—Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Brotherly—Friends.</hi> Let vs bee <hi>Brethren</hi> like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in this chapter verſe 26. <hi>O let vs not wrong one another.</hi> Let vs be <hi>Friends</hi> like <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. Let vs knit our <hi>Soules</hi> together, and let vs be <hi>Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Friends</hi> like the <hi>Epheſians, Eph.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Labouring to keepe the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> Let vs be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> amongſt our ſelues, <hi>men of one heart, and of one minde,</hi> and then doubt we not, our <hi>one</hi> God, wil preſerue vs from all our enemies.</p>
                  <p>And where the <hi>heart</hi> doth command,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the <hi>feete</hi> will be pliable: It followeth therefore, <hi>they ranne vpon him. They ranne</hi>—yea and more alſo: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>impetus,</hi> they <hi>ranne impetiouſly</hi> vpon him. A military metaphor: As a companie aſſignd to aſſault a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, ſuddainely caſt themſelues into the ditch (like one globe) and immediately climbe the breach with a thronging violence: ſo did theſe Iewes poſt vnto their bloody execution. Wee haue the like phraſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.32. the heard of ſwine, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from a ſteepe rock <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they <hi>powred</hi> themſelues into the ſea: like a thicke cloude diſſoluing it ſelfe into a ſhowre, where euery droppe ſtriuing to out ſtrip his fellow, the firſt ſeemeth to be laſt, and the laſt to bee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3231:31"/>firſt, the whole falling downe at one inſtant: ſo theſe <hi>ranne</hi> with expedition. The poets faine that <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> (their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oote poſt of heauen) had <hi>wings at his heeles,</hi> indeede theſe perſecuters <hi>ranne with winged ſpeede,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh, their <hi>feete were ſwift to ſhedde blood,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they <hi>ranne,</hi> and the blood of S. <hi>Steuen</hi> was the <hi>goale</hi> they <hi>ranne</hi> to.</p>
                  <p>Apparent therefore it is,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                     </label> that the <hi>wicked will take paines to miſchiefe the godly.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they <hi>ranne</hi> vpon S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Luke. Math.</hi> 23.15. Hypocrites will trauell a <hi>large compaſſe,</hi> to bring one within the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of damnation. Improbus labor — infinite</hi> is the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the <hi>impious.</hi> So <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth that hee was <hi>hunted</hi> by his perſecuters: Indeede <hi>Hounds,</hi> in hope to be fleſhed at the fall of the game, will purſue it with indefatigable nimbleneſſe: and it is their <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime to take paines for blood.</hi> So theſe ſage Phariſies, who another time, would pace in a plaine roade, as the old greeke did climbe the craggie mountaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they would haue thought that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle way, had coſt them great labour. Now ſo ſoone as they ſent their game, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>they ranne—they ranne vpon their pray.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If they take ſo much <hi>paines to runne</hi> on vs,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> let vs take as much <hi>paines</hi> to withſtand their <hi>ſhock.</hi> Let vs carefully arme our ſelues with the <hi>breaſt-plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>ſword of the Spirit:</hi> Let vs labour for <hi>intelligience</hi> to <hi>know</hi> the Scriptures, &amp; for <hi>innocence to practiſe</hi> the Scriptures. Thus if we haue illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our <hi>heads and ſanctification in our hearts:</hi> wee ſhall be <hi>Barricadoed,</hi> and <hi>Palizadoed</hi> againſt their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3231:32"/>careere. They ſhall <hi>runne on vs,</hi> as the <hi>hounds</hi> doe on the <hi>horned ſtagge,</hi> and as the <hi>horſe</hi> on the <hi>armed pikes:</hi> they runne to their owne death, to their owne deſtruction. Wicked men may <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>They may runne on vs on euery ſide, but in the name of the Lord we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that it may appeare that they were <hi>armed,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>cap a pe:</hi> that their whole <hi>Body</hi> might be imbrued in blood: they ſet to their <hi>Hands</hi> alſo — <hi>many hands — many hands to make lewde worke.</hi> Firſt they forced his <hi>body</hi> out of the <hi>citty,</hi> then his <hi>ſoule</hi> out of his <hi>body:</hi> the text ſaith, <hi>they caſt him out of the citty and ſtoned him.</hi> In both as <hi>lawleſſe</hi> as they were <hi>Barbarous:</hi> in the firſt they offended againſt their <hi>owne law,</hi> their <hi>owne law</hi> was, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.50. that they ſhould haue beene <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they ſhould haue <hi>brought him,</hi> not <hi>caſt</hi> him <hi>out of the citty.</hi> In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond againſt the <hi>Romane law,</hi> as they themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.31. It is not <hi>lawfull</hi> for vs (being <hi>vaſſels to Rome</hi>) to put any man to death. But they acted both in a franticke tumult: the <hi>Preſident</hi> politickly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fire to come from <hi>Millo</hi> to conſume <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> and reciprocally from <hi>Abimelech</hi> to conſume <hi>Millo</hi> that a rebellious people might deuoure one another, the <hi>Preſident</hi> with coniuence cloſed his eyes, againſt this, and ſuch like <hi>law-leſſe</hi> vproares.</p>
                  <p>Where we cannot but take notice of another pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of <hi>Perſecuters:
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                        </label> Their malice is vnlimited,</hi> no <hi>law</hi> can repreſſe them. In the text, to worke their venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they regard neither the <hi>law of Iſrael,</hi> nor that of <hi>Rome,</hi> but deſperately infringe both the one, and the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3231:32"/>other. And indeed the grand-perſecuter, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a <hi>lawleſſe</hi> vſurper. <hi>Dauid</hi> did experience this qualitie from <hi>Perſecuting Saul:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>law of nature,</hi> (for hee was his <hi>kinſeman</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>law of the nation,</hi> (for he was his <hi>King</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>law of Matrimonie,</hi> (for he was his <hi>Father:</hi>) againſt the <hi>law of Religion,</hi> (for he confeſſed <hi>Dauid</hi> to be more <hi>righteous</hi> then himſelfe) yet againſt <hi>all law</hi> did he <hi>proſecute</hi> his <hi>lawleſſe perſecution.</hi> Wee may eaſily conceiue the cauſe. <hi>Perſecuters</hi> haue their <hi>eies blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot</hi> (they ſacrifice to their <hi>malice</hi> (what the old <hi>Gaules</hi> did to <hi>Eſus</hi> and <hi>Teutatus Lactant.</hi> 1.21. <hi>cruorem huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> the goare of <hi>men</hi>) <hi>Blood</hi> ſeeleth vp their <hi>eyes,</hi> they cannot, they will not ſee heauen nor earth: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like the <hi>vniuſt Iudge, Luk.</hi> 18.2. <hi>they feare neither God nor man,</hi> No <hi>Law</hi> can binde them, no bonds can reſtraine them.</p>
                  <p>From theſe premiſes,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> conclude with a <hi>rare reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> we may expect from <hi>Rome,</hi> if our <hi>reconcilers</hi> proiect might be imbraced. What <hi>Law</hi> can protect vs from <hi>Perſecution?</hi> If we dare <hi>imbrace</hi> with <hi>Ioab, feaſt</hi> with <hi>Abſolon, ſleepe</hi> with <hi>Iaell,</hi> and <hi>marry</hi> with <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ui,</hi> then may we be <hi>reconciled to Rome.</hi> But as for <hi>Lawes, vowes, others, promiſes, proteſtations, &amp;c.</hi> Such <hi>bonds</hi> they can breake them, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his <hi>cords,</hi> with an eaſie nimble dexteritie. And they haue <hi>reaſon</hi> for it, <hi>propter bonum eccleſiae,</hi> for the <hi>good of the Catholike cauſe:</hi> it is a reſolued caſe, by a religious councell, <hi>fides non eſt ſeruanda cum hoereticis,</hi> it is <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to ruine heretikes, by any graceleſſe <hi>lawleſſe</hi> meanes. But I truſt God will not permit vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3231:33"/>our ſelues into the <hi>hands</hi> of thoſe <hi>blood-ſeeking, blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucking perſecuters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of their <hi>perſecution—execution</hi> how they <hi>ſtoned</hi> him: I his point hath beene ſo ſufficiently ſearched into, by the learned and laboured ſermon of my predeceſſour in this place, on this day, laſt yeare: that I may truly ſay he hath not <hi>left one ſtone</hi> (for my labour) <hi>vnremooued.</hi> Truſting therefore that your <hi>memory</hi> is ſomewhat anſwerable <hi>to his labour,</hi> I will <hi>paſſe</hi> it beeing aſſured that I cannot <hi>paſſe him.</hi> Though the <hi>time be Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe,</hi> yet the point ſhall be a <hi>Paſſe-ouer;</hi> I will omit <hi>tautologies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> from theſe <hi>fiue points,</hi> haue ye heard how theſe <hi>Perſecuters</hi> were armed for <hi>blood at all points:</hi> Now ſuppoſe ye ſee them in their <hi>Campur Martius,</hi> trooped out to giue the terrible on ſet. The <hi>Seene</hi> lyeth at <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> and without the <hi>walles</hi> thereof their <hi>Aceldama,</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> where they acted this bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die tragedie was <hi>without the cittie</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they <hi>caſt him out of the citty</hi> ſaith my text.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>point</hi> is like <hi>Rebeckaes wombe, Gen.</hi> 25.23. it doth <hi>twinne:</hi> obſerue here two things. Firſt, the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of perſecuters. Secondly, the <hi>reward</hi> of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters.</p>
                  <p>It is the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Perſecuters</hi> to pretend equitie and <hi>law</hi> for their <hi>perſecution.</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>1</label> Theſe <hi>Perſecuters</hi> in and <hi>law</hi> for their <hi>perſecution.</hi> Theſe <hi>Perſecuters</hi> in the text, pleade the very ſame. The <hi>Place (without the cittie)</hi> the <hi>law</hi> did preſcribe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.5. the <hi>Action, (to ſtone the Blaſphemer)</hi> that <hi>law</hi> did permit it. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24.16. Crimes moſt <hi>lawleſſe,</hi> muſt be <hi>countenanced</hi> by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3231:33"/>the law notwithſtanding. This is no noueltie: Chriſt foretold long ſince that <hi>ſome</hi> ſhould <hi>thinke</hi> (therefore <hi>all</hi> ſhould <hi>ſay</hi>) <hi>that they did God ſeruice in klling his ſeruants, Ioh.</hi> 16.2. that it was <hi>aequum &amp; bonum,</hi> that their <hi>Perſecution</hi> was according to <hi>law</hi> and <hi>equitie.</hi> And Chriſt felt in himſelfe what hee foretold to others, <hi>nos legem habemus, we haue a law, and by that law</hi> he ought to <hi>die. Ioh.</hi> 19.7. Which pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous probleme hath ſince beene ſpit out of the mouth of <hi>Machiavell</hi> himſelfe: to <hi>ſeeme religious</hi> is <hi>profitable</hi> (ſaith he) but to <hi>be</hi> religious is <hi>cumberſome. Diuels</hi> therefore will <hi>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nge</hi> themſelues into <hi>Angels of light:</hi> and that <hi>Diuelliſh Perſecution,</hi> may put on the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Angelicall equitie,</hi> they plead the <hi>Law</hi> for it: this is the <hi>Nature of Perſecuters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mee thinkes,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> this may <hi>coole our Salamanders</hi> who delight to <hi>liue</hi> in the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Law:</hi> Euen, both the <hi>quarrelſome cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt,</hi> and the <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nning Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſeller,</hi> the firſt bringeth <hi>ſuell,</hi> and the other <hi>breath</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that <hi>fire,</hi> which hath <hi>conſumed</hi> many an <hi>houſe,</hi> in our little Iſland. <hi>Yee doe but what is Law!</hi> is <hi>that a Law for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>our ooings?</hi> what if the extent of <hi>Law</hi> may put a <hi>ſtone into thy hand:</hi> — Wilt thou? — Oh will thou <hi>Braine Steu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> and ruine thy poore bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Thou ſeeſt that theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> in the text were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Doctors of the Law:</hi> theſe <hi>great Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> were <hi>great Lawyers:</hi> and may not <hi>great Lawyers be great Perſecuters?</hi> Let not the <hi>Law</hi> out-ſtrippe thy <hi>Conſcience:</hi> leaſt all thy actions prooue <hi>vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>lawleſſe</hi> alſo: and the <hi>proſecution</hi> of thy cauſe the <hi>perſecution</hi> of thy brother. How many tragicke
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3231:34"/>tones haue groaned out the comicke phraſe: <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ius eſt ſumma iniuria,</hi> that the <hi>extremitie</hi> of <hi>law,</hi> is a <hi>lawleſſe extremitie.</hi> Let me tell thy <hi>conſcience:</hi> If thy <hi>conſcience</hi> tell thee, that thou art the <hi>Plaintife</hi> through raking <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi> the <hi>Defendant</hi> through proud <hi>obſtinateneſſe,</hi> or the <hi>Counceller, Pleader</hi> or <hi>Iudge,</hi> for thy <hi>fees</hi> onely: deſiring to <hi>feele</hi> the cauſe for thy owne <hi>benefit,</hi> and not to <hi>ſee</hi> the equitie thereof, though it be for thy owne <hi>preiudice.</hi> Then doe I ſay, <hi>legem habitis, yee haue a Law,</hi> and according to that <hi>Law</hi> yee ſhall <hi>die:</hi> your owne <hi>law</hi> ſhall ſtand vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you before the <hi>great Iudge.</hi> Till then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber but this: It is the <hi>Nature of perſecuters</hi> to <hi>pretend law for their perſecution.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But whatſoeuer the <hi>Nature</hi> of them is,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>2</label> the <hi>Reward of perſecuters</hi> is moſt iuſt and righteous. Oftentimes <hi>perſecutors are puniſhed in the ſame things, which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon others.</hi> Theſe Iewes did <hi>caſt</hi> this <hi>Saint</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>out of the citty,</hi> and they themſelues were after <hi>caſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, by the <hi>Romanes</hi> were they <hi>caſt out of the citty:</hi> They became <hi>palabundi, coeli &amp; ſoli profugi</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> the <hi>out-caſts</hi> of all the <hi>out-coaſts</hi> of the earth. Gods iuſt iudgement denounced, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you:</hi> It is not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Reuenge,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>a Talio, like for like</hi> as we vſe to ſpeake, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as <hi>Theodoret</hi> elegantly: <hi>whereby thou haſt</hi> offended, <hi>Thereby thou art offended.</hi> Of theſe very Iewes it is obſerued in another caſe, that after they had <hi>ſtoned Steuen,</hi> they became yet more <hi>ſtony hearted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3231:34"/>Lapides Iudae a rebellis, In Stephanum limphata rapis, quae crimine duro Saxea ſemper eris. <hi>ſaith</hi> Royard <hi>out of</hi> Aratus.</q>
                  <p>When the ſhowre of <hi>ſtones</hi> were powred out of the hands of theſe <hi>perſecuters,</hi> on the body of this <hi>Martyr,</hi> one <hi>ſtone</hi> did <hi>rebound</hi> from his bodie and ſmote—not the <hi>Elbow</hi> of a profeſſour, as the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> rarely ſporte themſelues (with a fable out <hi>Pſeude Auguſtine:</hi> but ſurely it ſmote the <hi>hearts</hi> of all thoſe <hi>perſecuters</hi> whence al the Iewes haue euer ſince haue bin ſo <hi>ſtony hearted,</hi> reſiſting the truth with a brow of braſſe and bowels of <hi>Adamant.</hi> So alſo <hi>Adonibezech</hi> forcing his captiues to gather their crummes vnder his table, with their fingers and thumbes cut of, was forced himſelfe to feede in the ſame faſhion. <hi>Haman</hi> tooke great care to erect a <hi>Gallowes</hi> for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and he had the honour to climbe them in his owne perſon. In infinite particulars hath God <hi>paide perſecuters</hi> in their <hi>owne coine:</hi> according to that prime axiome in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticke diuinitie, <hi>Quod tibi fieri non vis alteri ne feceris: Doe as thou wouldest be done vnto.</hi> Hence doth the Lord frequently—righteouſly permit that the <hi>ſame Viper</hi> ſhall eate out the bowels of her <hi>Damme,</hi> and haue her bowels eaten out of her <hi>yong:</hi> that the <hi>Hauke</hi> ſhould purſue the <hi>Patridge,</hi> and the <hi>Aegle</hi> the <hi>Hauke:</hi> that the <hi>perſecuters</hi> ſhould bee <hi>perſecuted</hi> in the <hi>ſame kinde,</hi> wherein they <hi>perſecuted</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>one</hi> conſideration,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> is a ſufficient <hi>Antidote</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3231:35"/>many ſinnes; if there were neither heauen, nor hell to perſwade vs. This very <hi>talio</hi> may deterre vs from beeing <hi>tales:</hi> that God will requite ſinners in <hi>their kinde,</hi> in the <hi>ſame kinde,</hi> that themſelues tranſgreſſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Defile</hi> not therefore thy ſoule by <hi>defiling</hi> thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours bedde with <hi>Adulterie:</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label> leaſt the <hi>Adulterers</hi> ſpawne robbe thy <hi>legitimate</hi> children, and that thou take great paines, to bring vp a <hi>Baſiard</hi> to ſucceede thee in thy inheritance. Vſe not <hi>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe dealing</hi> in thy trade: leaſt <hi>falſe dealers, falſe traders, and falſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,</hi> cauſe thee to crie for bread through a grate in an aged beggary. Triumph not in thy <hi>couragious quarrels,</hi> that thou haſt come of from one fight with <hi>honour:</hi> for a ſecond <hi>Duell</hi> may <hi>lay thy honour in the duſt, and Cales ſands</hi> may be thy <hi>graue to bury</hi> thee. If <hi>Cyrus</hi> make the <hi>Scythian</hi> Prince to <hi>bleede, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mris</hi> may thruſt his <hi>head</hi> into a <hi>veſſellef blood.</hi> Grinde not the face of the poore by griping <hi>vſury:</hi> leaſt the Lord make thy wife a widdow, and that the <hi>extortioner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure thy children.</hi> Swell not with <hi>pride</hi> through thy <hi>preferment, to contemne thine inferiours:</hi> know (that the ſeede of <hi>Eli,</hi> may bow to <hi>Zadocke</hi> for a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of bread) that thy poſteritie may crouch to him, who ſitteth in the ſame ſeate which their father once poſſeſſed. Set not thine <hi>hand</hi> nor <hi>finger,</hi> (much leſſe your <hi>heads or ſhoulders</hi> (to ouerthrow the Church, or to impoueriſh the impoueriſhes cleargy. Why man! Thou art neither <hi>omnipotent</hi> nor <hi>omniſcient:</hi> by no <hi>prouiſion</hi> canſt thou <hi>foreſay,</hi> by no <hi>praeuiſion</hi> canſt thou <hi>foreſee,</hi> what the calling of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3231:35"/>thine owne ſhall be. It may bee thine <hi>owne childe,</hi> or thy <hi>childes childe,</hi> may be called <hi>to ſerue at the Alter,</hi> to be a <hi>poore—ſo poore</hi> a Leuite, that while he liueth if he ſhould <hi>ſell</hi> his wife and children, all would not ſatisfie the <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke ſeller:</hi> and when hee doth die, his diſtreſſed widdow, and beggared <hi>Orphans,</hi> though charitie be in their <hi>hearts,</hi> yet their <hi>loines</hi> may <hi>curſe</hi> the memorie of. all <hi>Church-robbers:</hi> when their owne <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Fore-fathers,</hi> haue beene the ringe-leaders of that <hi>curſed generation.</hi> In a word: Be no <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter,</hi> leaſt thou be <hi>Perſecuted:</hi> be no <hi>Iewes,</hi> leaſt yee be vſed like <hi>Iewes: Throw</hi> not a <hi>ſtone</hi> at poore <hi>Steuen,</hi> leaſt it rebound on thine owne <hi>head.</hi> And caſt not an innocent <hi>out of the citty,</hi> leaſt thou thy ſelfe bee caſt out of the <hi>country.</hi> There is a iuſt ludge who will recompence euill to euill men in the ſame kinde that they themſelues did practiſe it.</p>
                  <p>From the <hi>Place,</hi> proceed wee vnto the <hi>Perſon,</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and then I will requite your attention, with a ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. The <hi>Perſon</hi> is the <hi>Saint of this day,</hi> S. <hi>Steuen</hi> implied in the text by a threefold ingemination: <hi>They ranne vpon Him, they caſt out Him,</hi> and they <hi>ſtoned Him</hi>—firſt the man which <hi>preached to them: verſe</hi> 54. ſecondly, the man which <hi>prayed for them, verſe</hi> 60. thirdly, the man which was <hi>full of the holy Ghoſt, verſe</hi> 55. So that he might exclaime with <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> (murdered by the <hi>Senatours</hi>) <hi>Etiamtu fili?</hi> the <hi>children</hi> to murder their <hi>ſpirituall Father:</hi> the people to martyr their <hi>Saintlike Brother:</hi> and the profeſſed <hi>holy Iſraelites,</hi> ſeruants to the <hi>holy God,</hi> to ſtone an <hi>holy</hi> Saint, <hi>full</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghoſt!</hi>—We may (like
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3231:36"/>
                     <hi>Agamemnon</hi> at the ſacrificing of his daughter <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>) wee may <hi>draw a curtaine before our conceits, our imagination</hi> cannot behold ſo ſauage a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</p>
                  <p>Let vs remember this laſt inſtruction,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">doct. </seg>
                     </label> euen to our <hi>laſt</hi> day. <hi>Inraged Perſecuters are pittileſſe.</hi> I hey haue not onely a <hi>wooluiſh antipathy to ſhedde</hi> blood: but alſo a <hi>ſtoicoll apathy,</hi> to diſtinquiſh of no perſons in their cruell effuſion. As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> without <hi>naturall affection.</hi> In the text <hi>Steuen</hi> that was <hi>preaching,</hi> they murdered <hi>Him: Steuen</hi> that was <hi>praying,</hi> they murdered <hi>Him:</hi> and Saint <hi>Steuen,</hi> they murdered <hi>Him:</hi> yea had the quinteſſence of all <hi>ſanctitie, pietie, and caeleſtiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie</hi> beene treaſured vp in him alone, yet would they haue murdered <hi>Him: Math.</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 21. <hi>The Brother ſhall betray the Brother, the Father the Sonne, and the children ſhall riſe againſt the Parents, and cauſe them to die. Lurida terribiles miſcent aconita no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beriae:</hi> the perſecuting <hi>mothers,</hi> will take life <hi>from</hi> them, to whom they gaue life. <hi>Fratrum quo que gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia rara eſt,</hi> like the ſnakie iſſue of <hi>Cadmus Brethren deuoure</hi> one another. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was doubtleſſe an incomparable creature. <hi>Herod</hi> honoured him as a <hi>Saint,</hi> reuerenced him as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and obaied him as a <hi>Teacher!</hi> Yet when his barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous heart was fired, hee <hi>perſecuted Him,</hi> hee <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned Him,</hi> and hee <hi>beheaded Him.</hi> Moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for other ſinnes are bridled by <hi>ſhame,</hi> but <hi>Perſecution</hi> is <hi>ſpurred</hi> on by the repute of <hi>Sanctitie.</hi> This maketh <hi>Perſecuters,</hi> like <hi>Bandogges</hi> to ſeaze vpon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3231:36"/>the <hi>throate:</hi> like <hi>ſharpe-kept Haukes</hi> they will tyre on the <hi>Hart.</hi> The <hi>Perſecuter</hi> like <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 39. If any <hi>taſte the hony</hi> of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>though it bee Ionathan my ſonne</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>euen hee ſhall die the death.</hi> Herein a <hi>Perſecuter</hi> is like <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> hee is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, neither <hi>Father</hi> nor <hi>Mother</hi> ſhall bee ſpared by the hand of inraged <hi>Perſecution.</hi> As the <hi>Adamant</hi> cannot bee <hi>ſoftned</hi> but with the <hi>blood of goates,</hi> ſo ſhall not they bee mollified but with the blood of <hi>Lambes,</hi> of innocent profeſſours. Heere Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> was the <hi>obiect, abiect, ſubiect</hi> of ſuch ſauage impiety, they <hi>ranne vpon Him, they caſt out Him, and they ſtoned Him,</hi> ſaith my text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14.31.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>The king ſate downe and tooke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> whether hee were able <hi>to meete the twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand which came againſt him.</hi> Euery member of the Militant Church muſt aſſure himſelfe of <hi>twentie thouſand afflictions,</hi> which will come againſt him. <hi>Religion</hi> is a <hi>iewell,</hi> and wee muſt <hi>ſell</hi> all wee haue to purchaſe it. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>Spouſe:</hi> and wee muſt <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Father and Mother to cleaue to him.</hi> Let vs therefore in the name of God, <hi>ſit downe and take counſell,</hi> how wee may bee able to with-ſtand thoſe thouſands of temptations. But infinite wonder it is to ſee, how wee grumble at toyes and trifling trials. For euery <hi>ſlaunder of our inferiour,</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>ſupplanting of our Equall,</hi> and for euery <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace</hi> from our <hi>Superiour</hi> — oh —wee ſtartle, as if this were the <hi>ſtoning of Steuen,</hi> and the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3231:37"/>combate of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> The <hi>childe</hi> in the nurces armes, the <hi>touch of a pinne</hi> maketh it crie out as if it were <hi>killed:</hi> and the <hi>Free-Booter</hi> ſtandeth at the doore, breaketh into the childe, daſheth his braines againſt the ground, and then <hi>killeth him indeede.</hi> Such <hi>children are wee:</hi> euery <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our bodie,</hi> euery <hi>impoueriſhment of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> euery <hi>death of a deare friend,</hi> euery <hi>little—little diſcomfort,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, howe it <hi>woundeth</hi> our <hi>Hearts?</hi> it maketh vs to <hi>crie and raue and repine,</hi> when wee know not how neere the <hi>Free-Booter</hi> is vnto vs. It may thoſe very hands, which brought kniues for vs by <hi>ſea,</hi> and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fire for vs by <hi>land,</hi> thoſe very hands it may bee, are now a <hi>gathering ſtones for vs,</hi> watching for the firſt watch-word of fitte opportunitie. Wee muſt expect it: Wee haue had <hi>Halcyon daies of an Aegles age:</hi> after a <hi>calme,</hi> may come a <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt.</hi> Let this bee our reſolution: <hi>Scipio</hi> poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his armie, ſaid there was not <hi>one,</hi> who would not <hi>throw himſelfe from the toppe of a Towre</hi> for loue of him: So ſhould we ſay that we would arme our ſelues euen <hi>to be throwne from the toppe of a Towre for the loue of Chriſt.</hi> And this is no noueltie: Wee are no better then <hi>Peter,</hi> wee may bee <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned:</hi> wee are no better then <hi>Paul,</hi> wee may bee <hi>ſcourged:</hi> wee are no better then <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> wee may bee <hi>headed:</hi> and I thinke Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> was as good as moſt of vs: therefore wee may bee <hi>ſtoned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3231:37"/>
                  <p>To conclude: <hi>Priſoning, Scourging, Heading, Stoning, Perſecuting</hi> may come will come. All which wee <hi>ſhould</hi> indure, all which (in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſtrengthening vs (wee <hi>ſhall</hi> indure! Let vs ſay it <hi>now with our tongues:</hi> and the Lord graunt wee may reſolue it, and <hi>performe it with our hearts for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata,</head>
            <p>In the epiſtle, Pagina ſecunda, linea <hi>9.</hi> prò declarari lege declarare. Linea <hi>24.</hi> pro ni lege in page <hi>4.</hi> line. <hi>9.</hi> for Aquinus read Aquinas, line <hi>18.</hi> for by read vp, page <hi>5.</hi> line <hi>21.</hi> for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum reade analyticam, Page <hi>7.</hi> line <hi>8.</hi> for euer reade euen. Page <hi>19.</hi> line <hi>9.</hi> for kingdome read king. Page <hi>28.</hi> line <hi>19.</hi> for ſpereſſet read ſperaſſet.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
